<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="letter-meta">
        <head>Letter 1 – June 11, 1597</head>
        <p><date when="1597-06-11">June 11, 1597</date></p>
        <p><placeName ref="#london">London</placeName></p>
        <p>
          <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ref="#chamberlain-john">John Chamberlain</persName>
              <date when="1597-06-11"/>
              <placeName ref="#london">London</placeName>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ref="#carleton-dudley">Dudley Carleton</persName>
              <placeName ref="#paris">Paris</placeName>
            </correspAction>
          </correspDesc>
        </p>
      </div>
    </front>

    <body>
      <div type="letter-text">
        <p>Goode Master Carleton, I know you looked long ere this to have heard from me, and so might you well have done, if Painter the post had not kept your letter of the eighth of May <note>The reference is to an earlier letter from Carleton delayed by the post.</note> till the sixth of this present June.</p>

        <p>I received a little billet before, by your sister Williams, <note>Elizabeth, wife of Alexander Williams.</note> in the way of an interim till you had better leisure, but presently upon it went to Askot <note>Ascott, Oxfordshire, home of Michael Dormer (knighted, 1604).</note> where I met with your brother Carleton <note>George Carleton of Huntercombe.</note> (coming from the burial of your uncle Goodwin <note>Son of John Goodwin and Carleton’s maternal uncle.</note>), who told me Tobie Mathew <note>Later Archbishop of York.</note> had showed him a letter from you wherein you complained much of want, and what narrow straits you were likely to be driven to.</p>

        <p>Whereupon I gathered that his intention was to move me in your behalf, as indeed it was, and I was glad of it, as a good occasion, both to show my love to you, and to satisfy myself in that I have so long owed you; so that if you may be content to have so little, you shall not utterly want, as long as I have.</p>

        <p>But I pray you, consider how much better it were for you to make the trial to your parents, who are much more bound to you, and better able than I am, for I confess it will go hard with me to perform what I promise.</p>

        <p>From London this longest day of 1597.</p>

        <p>Yours most assuredly,<br/>JOHN CHAMBERLAIN</p>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div type="editor-note">
        <head>Editor's Note</head>
        <p>This letter offers a vivid window into Chamberlain’s early correspondence with Dudley Carleton. It touches on military news from Ireland, preparations for the “Islands Voyage,” court gossip, and Chamberlain’s own pending journey. Notable are Chamberlain’s indirect counsel to Carleton regarding financial support, and his detailed intelligence-gathering style. This letter also signals Chamberlain’s early tendency to function as a political informant and social interpreter.</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
