<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Letter 1 – Financial Concerns, Court Gossip, and the Islands Voyage</title>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Brandon Taylor</name>
          <resp>Editor and Verifier</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Chamberlain Letters Project</publisher>
        <idno type="uri">https://earlymodernletters.org/letters/chamberlain-letter1.xml</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
  <bibl xml:id="mcclure1939">
    <author>John Chamberlain</author>
    <editor>Norman Egbert McClure</editor>
    <title>The Letters of John Chamberlain</title>
    <publisher>American Philosophical Society</publisher>
    <date>1939</date>
  </bibl>
    <note>This letter is also cited as [5. P. Dom., Elm., ccIx'm, pp.] in manuscript references.</note>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <correspDesc>
        <correspAction type="sent">
          <persName ref="#chamberlain-john">John Chamberlain</persName>
          <placeName ref="#london">London</placeName>
          <date when="1597-06-11"/>
        </correspAction>
        <correspAction type="received">
          <persName ref="#carleton-dudley">Dudley Carleton</persName>
          <placeName ref="#paris">Paris</placeName>
        </correspAction>
      </correspDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="letter-meta">
        <p>This digital edition is based on the transcription and annotations of Norman Egbert McClure’s 1939 edition of <title>The Letters of John Chamberlain</title>. This version has been edited and encoded for the Chamberlain Letters Project by <name type="editor">Brandon Taylor</name>.</p>
        <head>Letter 1 – Financial Concerns, Court Gossip, and the Islands Voyage</head>
        <p><date when="1597-06-11">June 11, 1597</date></p>
        <p><placeName ref="#london">London</placeName></p>
        <!-- correspDesc moved to teiHeader/profileDesc -->
      </div>
    </front>

    <body>
      <div type="letter-text">
        <opener>
          <salute>Goode Master [Dudley] Carleton,</salute>
        </opener>

        <seg type="topic" n="delay-in-correspondence"/>
        <p>
          I know you lookt longe ere this time to have 
          heard from me, and so might you well have don, yf Painter the post had 
          not kept your letter of the eight of May aseasoninge till the sixt of this 
          present June.
        </p>

        <seg type="topic" n="carleton-financial-report"/>
        <p>
          I received a litle billet before, by your sister Williams,<note><persName ref="#williams-elizabeth">Elizabeth</persName>, wife of <persName ref="#williams-alexander">Alexander Williams</persName>,</note>
          in the way of an interim till you had better leasure, but presently upon 
          yt went to Askot<note>Ascott, Oxfordshire, the home of <persName ref="#dormer-michael">Michael Dormer</persName> (knighted, 1604).</note> where I met with your brother <persName ref="#carleton-george">Carleton</persName><note><persName ref="#carleton-george">George Carleton</persName> of Huntercombe, Oxfordshire.</note> (comming from the buriall of your uncle Goodwin,)<note>Brother of Carleton's mother, and son of <persName ref="#goodwin-john">John Goodwin</persName>.</note> who told me <persName ref="#mathew-tobie">Tobie Mathew</persName><note>Knighted, 1623. Son of <persName ref="#matthew-tobias">Tobias Matthew</persName>, Bishop of Durham, and later Archbishop of York.</note> had shewed him a letter from you wherin you complained much of want, and what narrow straights you were like to be driven to, marvayling you 
          had toucht no such matter in your letters to him : and therewithall began 
          to dilate to me what he had don and could do for you, but the conclusion 
          was that his abilitie is not to supplie all wants, and therefore you must 
          trust to yourself and make your owne fortune. I replied litle to yt but 
          only in generall termes, the rather because I hope yt is but a borrowed 
          complaint to distast younge Mathew from following you into <placeName ref="#France">Fraunce</placeName>, then for any true cause.
        </p>

        <seg type="topic" n="ambassadorial-support-and-irish-news"/>
        <p>
          I am exceding glad to heare how well you are 
          entertained by my Lord Ambassador :<note><persName ref="#mildmay-anthony">Sir Anthony Mildmay</persName>, ambassador to Henry IV.</note> of whom I presumed no lesse, for 
          though I alwayes knewe him to be <hi rend="italics" xml:lang="la">paucorum hominem</hi>, yet he hath ever shewed himself an honorable fast frend where he found vertue and desert. Master <persName ref="#unknown-evers">Evers</persName><!-- Uncertain identity, a relation of Ralph Eure but unclear.--><note>Cousin of <persName ref="#eure-ralph">Ralph</persName>, third Lord Eure or Evers, Lord Warden of the Middle Marches.</note> is in Ireland with the Lord <persName ref="#burgh-thomas">Borrough</persName><!--Thomas Burgh, 1st Baron Burgh is listed on Wikipedia but this does not seem to be him.--><note>Thomas, fifth Lord Burgh, appointed Lord Deputy of Ireland in 1597.</note> between whom and Sir John Norris<note>Lord President of Munster, second son of Henry, first Lord Norris of Rycote.</note> there is lately a solemne pacification made with much counterfet kindenes on both sides. The old Deputie<note>Sir William Russell (created Lord Russell of Thornhaugh, 1603), fourth son of Francis, second Earl of Bedford. He was Lord Deputy from 1594 to 1597. "Russell was called home; and in his place was substituted Lord Deputy Thomas Lord Borrough, a sharp man, and full of courage, but of little skill in the warres; and this beyond the opinion of all men, and altogether against the expectation of Norris, who in respect of his deserts, and skill in military matters, had promised to himselfe this place. . . and now overcome with griefe of minde, fell sicke, and shortly after died." (Camden, <hi rend="italics">Annales</hi>, p. 482.) Queen Elizabeth wrote his mother a beautiful letter of condolence, September 22, 1597. (S. P. Dom. Eliz., cclxiv, 118.)</note> is come home very fat they say both in body and purse, having made a luckie conclusion of his government with the overthrow and death of Feff Mackhugh<note>At the Glynnes, May 8, Feogh MacHugh was captured and his head presented to the Lord Deputy. (Sir William Russell's Journal in <hi rend="italics">Carew MSS., 1598-1600</hi>, p. 259.)</note> auncient and troublesom rebell : upon which service he made three knightes at his comming away, viz. Calistenes Brooke, Thomas Maria Wingfeld, and one Trevire<note>Sir Calisthenies Brooke, Sir Thomas Maria Wingfield, and Sir Richard Trevor were knighted May 8.</note> a Welchman. Sir Thomas Norris<note>Fifth son of Henry, first Lord Norris of Rycote. Later in the year he succeeded his brother as Lord President of Munster.</note> lady was lately brought abed there of three daughters, which the Lord Norris<note>Henry Lord Norris of Rycote.</note> imputes to the fertilitie of the soyle, and exemplifies yt by a mare he sent two yeares ago to his sonne Thomas that brought two foales.
        </p>

        <seg type="topic" n="islands-voyage-planning"/>
        <p>
          We have great preparation here for a sea viage,<note>The expedition usually known as the Islands Voyage. The leaders hoped to destroy the Spanish war fleet in the harbor of Ferrol or at sea, to capture the treasure and merchant fleets from the West and East Indies, and to establish a foothold in the Azores. Their plans failed, and in October they returned to England.</note> which 
          troubles our discoursers how or where yt shalbe imployed : the common 
          sort talke of Callais, others of the ylands of Tercera, but the most likelie 
          in mine opinion, is to set upon the King of Spaines navie whersoever 
          they can finde yt, or to meet with the Indian fleet. Theyre whole num-
          ber consists of fifteen of the Quenes shippes, besides the two Spanish 
          shippes that were taken the last yeare, (which be new fashioned after the 
          English manner), and of two and twentie men of warre of Holland, 
          and some fowre and twentie flieboats and hoyes that serve for cariage of 
          men and vitayles. They have with them 4000 prest men, and 1200 
          muskettiers that come with Sir Fra: Vere out of the Low Countries: the 
          voluntaries are thought will rise towardes 2000. The erle of Essex<note>Robert Devereux, second Earl of Essex, Queen Elizabeth's troublesome young favorite.</note> 
          is generall both at sea and land, the Lord Thomas<note>Thomas Lord Howard of Walden (created Earl of Suffolk, 1603).</note> Viceadmirall, Sir Walter Raleigh<note>He had been forbidden the court because of his marriage five years before.</note> rereadmirall, who is newly restored to the executing 
          his place in court of captaine of the garde. The erle of Southampton,<note>Henry Wriothesley, third Earl of Southampton.</note> 
          the Lord Mountjoy<note>Charles Blount, eighth Lord Mountjoy (created Earl of Devonshire, 1603).</note> and the Lord Rich<note>Robert, third Lord Rich (created Earl of Warwick, 1618).</note> go as adventurers, though 
          some say the Lord Mountjoy is to be lieutenant-generall at land. The 
          erle of Darbie,<note>William Stanley, sixth Earl of Derby.</note> the Lord Gray,<note>Thomas, fifteenth Lord Grey of Wilton.</note> the Lords Windsor<note>Henry, fifth Lord Windsor of Stanwell.</note> and Compton<note>William, second Lord Compton (created Earl of Northampton, IMS).</note> 
          pretend likewise to go but yt is thought shall not get leave: the provisions 
          are hastened on very fast and yt is sayde the erle of Essex takes his leave 
          at court on Sonday next the 12th of this present and hopes to be gon 
          within ten dayes after.
        </p>

        <seg type="topic" n="islands-voyage-personnel"/>
        <p>
          The presse of gentlemen wilbe very great, but 
          I will not stand to set downe any but one or two of your acquaintaunce, 
          that is your cousin Mighell Dormer whom I can by no meanes yet disswade, and Hugh Beston<note>Hugh Beeston (knighted, 1603).</note> that stands to be Treasurer of the jorny 
          though I doubt he shall not be troubled with much receit, for I am half 
          of our Doctors<note>William Gilbert, who in 1601 became physician to Queen Elizabeth. At this time Chamberlain had lodgings in his house on St. Peter's Hill.</note> opinion that warrants him yf he have yt, that a well 
          sadled rat may cary all his accompts. But his true errand is to be 
          knighted assone or before Sir Peter Evers,<note>Knighted, 1603.</note> neither doth he dissemble 
          yt greatly to his frends but sayes merelie he hath ben a scabd squire a 
          great while, and could now be content to be a paltrie knight the rest of 
          his time. Sir John North<note>Son of Roger, second Lord North. His wife was Dorothy, daughter of Sir Valentine Dale.</note> died here on Sonday last, and is thought to 
          have left his lady but a meane widowe. Sir Thomas Wroughton<note>Of Broad Hinton, Wiltshire.</note> went 
          likewise much about the same time, and old Duns<note>Presumably Edmund Dunche of Wittenham, Berkshire, father of William Dunche. Cf. Letter 17.</note> when I was in Oxfordshire.
        </p>

        <seg type="topic" n="court-deaths-and-social-news"/>
        <p>
          John Payton is lately made lieutenant of the Towre, and Sir Henry Cocke either is or upon the point to be sworne Coferer of the Quenes houshold. Phillip Scudamore<note>Knighted, 1603.</note> is very forward and like to have Mistris Lovell<note>Dorothy, daughter of Michael Greene, and widow of Gregory Lovell, Cofferer of the Royal Household.</note> the last Coferers widow, to the great dislike of some of his best frends. And your Lady Umpton<note>Dorothy, daughter of Sir Thomas Wroughton, and widow of Sir Henry Unton, who died ambassador to France, March 23 1596. She became Shirley's second wife. August 3, 1598., Carleton wrote Chamberlain, "I have been at Broad Hinton and stayed four days with Lady Unton, who beautifies her sorrow with all the ornaments of an honorable widow." (S. P. Dom., Eliz., cclir, 93.)</note> is in parlee with Master George Sherly of Northampton or Lecestershire. This term here was one Longe a captaine of Somersetshire condemned in the Star-chamber in 500 markes and to stand on the pillorie for chopping and making portsale<note>Public sale to the highest bidder.</note> of his souldiers.
        </p>

        <seg type="topic" n="london-theatre-and-ireland-trip"/>
        <p>
          We have here a new play of humors<note>Probably "The Comedy of Umers" mentioned by Henslowe and performed nine times during May and June by the Admiral's Men at the Rose. Henslowe's play was almost certainly Chapman's <hi rend="italics">An Humorous Day's Mirth</hi>, the earliest extant play of this type. (Greg, <hi rend="italics">Henslowe's Diary</hi>, i, 52 <hi rend="italics" xml:lang="la">et passim</hi>; Schelling, <hi rend="italics">Elizabethan Drama</hi>, i, 460; Parrott, <hi rend="italics">Comedies of George Chapman</hi>, p. 685; Chambers, <hi rend="italics">Elizabethan Stage</hi>, iii, 251.)</note> in very great request, and I was drawn alonge to yt by the common applause, but my opinion of yt is (as the fellow sayde of the shearing of hogges) that there was a great crie for so litle wolle. This is all I can bethincke me of for the present neither can you chuse but be reasonablie satisfied, for what you want in waight you have in measure. Yet is the greatest newes behinde that I am upon a viage into Ireland with  Master Wallop,<note>Henry Wallop (knighted, 1599). His father, Sir Henry Wallop, was then Vice-Treasurer of Ireland. His wife was Elizabeth, daughter of Robert Corbet of Morton-Corbet, Shropshire. Her mother was Anne, daughter of Oliver Lord St. John, widow of Robert Corbet, and wife of Rowland Lytton (knighted, 1603) of Knebworth. Lytton's mother was Anne Carleton, aunt of Dudley Carleton.</note> who with his wife, her mother, and your cousen Lytton have so earnestly intreated me, that partly at theyre request and partly being weary of ydlenes I have yeelded, and hope to be setting forward within this moneth and to be here againe before Bartlemewtide.
        </p>

        <seg type="topic" n="farewell-and-family-update"/>
        <p>
          You be like enough to heare of me before I go yf here be ought worth writing. Your sister Alice is close prisoner at her ladies; the rest of your frends are in state as you left them and so wishing you all health and goode hap I bid you farewell. From London this longest day of 1597.
        </p>

        <closer>
          <salute rend="right">Yours most assuredly,</salute>
          <signed rend="right">JOHN CHAMBERLAIN</signed>
        </closer>

        <postscript>
          <address>To my assured good frend Master Dudley Carleton attendaunt on the Lord Ambassador for her Majestie at Paris.</address>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div type="editor-note">
        <head>Editor's Note</head>
        <p>This letter offers a vivid window into Chamberlain’s early correspondence with Dudley Carleton. Written from London on June 11, 1597, it addresses Carleton’s financial worries, relayed through a report from his brother about a letter shown by Tobie Mathew. Chamberlain tactfully avoids direct comment, suggesting the complaint may have been strategic. The letter also includes intelligence on Irish military affairs, particularly the return of Sir William Russell and the death of Feogh MacHugh, along with preparations for the Islands Voyage, a planned naval expedition against Spanish forces. Court news features prominently, including the deaths of several figures, a set of new appointments, and social gossip involving marriages and ambitions. Chamberlain concludes with his own decision to travel to Ireland with the Wallop and Lytton families. Throughout, he demonstrates his emerging role as an informal correspondent and observer of political and social developments.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="notes"/>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
