<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Letter 2 – Foreign Diplomacy, Irish Disorder, and Domestic Unrest</title>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Brandon Taylor</name>
          <resp>Editor and Verifier</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Chamberlain Letters Project</publisher>
        <idno type="uri">https://earlymodernletters.org/letters/chamberlain-letter[#].xml</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl xml:id="mcclure1939">
          <author>John Chamberlain</author>
          <editor>Norman Egbert McClure</editor>
          <title>The Letters of John Chamberlain</title>
          <publisher>American Philosophical Society</publisher>
          <date>1939</date>
        </bibl>
        <note>[Optional manuscript source note, if available]</note>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <correspDesc>
        <correspAction type="sent">
          <persName ref="#chamberlain-john">John Chamberlain</persName>
          <placeName ref="#london">London</placeName>
          <date when="YYYY-MM-DD"/>
        </correspAction>
        <correspAction type="received">
          <persName ref="#carleton-dudley">Dudley Carleton</persName>
          <placeName ref="#paris">Paris</placeName>
        </correspAction>
      </correspDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="editor-note">
        <head>Editorial Status</head>
        <p>This transcription is provisional. The text has been input but not yet fully edited or annotated. Interpretive notes, proper name tagging, and corrections will follow in a later revision.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="letter-meta">
        <p>This digital edition is based on the transcription and annotations of Norman Egbert McClure’s 1939 edition of <title>The Letters of John Chamberlain</title>. This version has been edited and encoded for the Chamberlain Letters Project by <name type="editor">Brandon Taylor</name>.</p>
        <head>Letter 2 – Foreign Diplomacy, Irish Disorder, and Domestic Unrest</head>
        <p><date when="YYYY-MM-DD">[1598-05-04]</date></p>
        <p><placeName ref="#london">London</placeName></p>
      </div>
    </front>

    <body>
      <div type="letter-text">

        <!-- Repeat as needed: -->
        <seg type="topic" n="visit-to-knebworth-and-household-absence"/>
        <p>
          I am newly returned from Knebworth,1 whence I made the more
           haste that I might aunswer your letter from Ostend of the 9th of Aprill.
           I wrote to you much about the time of your departure, which how yt
           came to your handes God knowes, as likewise what shall become of this,
           which I write at all adventures, for here is nothing but solitude ante
           ostium, nobody at home neither at your brother Williams 2 nor my Lady
           Northes.s Your sister Alice they say is in the country; belike there is
           somwhat a brewing, and this is all I can tell you of houshold matters.
        </p>
           
        <seg type="topic" n="carleton-military-career-and-retirement-advice"/>
        <p>
           Now touching your owne common wealth, I do not greatly like the
           course you are in, and yet hard beginnings commonly prove best, but
           still me thinckes you are out of your way as longe as you carry but the
           title of a souldier, and therfore unles your stomacke serve you the better,
           or that you see great probabilitie of well-doing, Cedant arma toga, retire
           in time, and yf nothing els will take, reserve that course for ultimum
           refugium at a dead lift.
           </p>
           
           <seg type="topic" n="return-of-secretary-and-health-of-his-father"/>
           <p>
            Master Secretary 4 returned the first of this
           moneth somwhat crased 5 with his posting jorny ; the report of his fathers
           daungerous estate gave him winges, but for ought I can learne the old
           mans case is not so desperate but he may hold out another yeare well
           inough. Most of his followers shipt themselves at Nantes and came
           away by longe seas, and were well coursed and almost taken by fowre
           or five Spanish shippes of Bluet, but yet arrived safely at Sandwich ;
           himself came overland to Caen and so to Portesmouth.
           </p>
           
           <seg type="topic" n="french-politics-and-anglo-dutch-strategy"/>
          <p>
           Dr. Harbert and his train are not yet come to towne but I heare they be in England.
           The successe of this jorny is not fully knowne but thus far, that yt hath
           staide the French king from going thorough with Spaine and made him
           pause at least. The States offer to maintaine him 4000 men in Picardie,
           which with litle other help will continue the warre there, now that he
           hath nothing to do elswhere. They have likewise offered the Quene
           that whensoever yt shall please her to make an invasive jorny into Spaine
           to assist her with great store of shipping at theyre owne charge some say
           to the number of 150 sayle. Yet for all this yt is still in deliberation
           whether we shall joyne with Fraunce in a peace and leave the Lowe
           Countries, or sticke to the Lowe Countries and hold out the warre, and
           the balaunce swayes not yet on either side, at leastwise that can be dis
           cerned. 
          </p>
           
          <seg type="topic" n="irish-crisis-and-failed-deputy-nominations"/>
          <p>
           Matters in Ireland are farther out of square then ever, so that
           there is no other way but to provide the sharper sword: here is speach
           of forces to be sent thether, but they cannot yet resolve upon a Deputie,
           for Sir Walter Raleigh, Sir Rob : Sidney a and Sir Christofer Blunt 7
           (as I heare) have refused yt.
           </p>
           
           <seg type="topic" n="conspiracy-against-queen-and-essex"/>
           <p>
           Here be certain apprehended for a con-
           spiracie against the Quenes person and my Lord of Essex, wherof one
           shold be a Scottishman or somwhat that way; much buzzing hath ben
           about yt, but either the matter is not ripe or there is somwhat els in
           yt, for yt is kept very secret.s
           </p> 
           
           <seg type="topic" n="alablaster-escape-and-snelling-execution"/>
           <p>
           Alablaster B that was clapt up for
           Poperie hath broken prison and got away: Snelling the ruffian that had
           the brabble with Charles Chester 10 had not so goode lucke, for on Mon
           day morning he went amayeng to Tiborne and was hangd there for a
           robberie committed about Highgate the Tewsday before.
           </p>
           
           <seg type="topic" n="deaths-of-legal-officers-and-succession"/>
           <p>
           I heare that
           Justice Beaumont11 and Sergeant Drew 12 that rode the northern circuit
           are bothe dead, upon some infection of the gayle as is most like. Like-
           wise Dr. Lewin that had the office of willes is lately dead, and one
           Dr. Gibson 14 that was Chauncellor of Yorke hath his place.
           </p> 
           
           <seg type="topic" n="muscovite-emperor-death-and-chaos"/>
           <p>
           The
           marchants have newes that the Emperor of Moscovie died in January
           last and that his wyfes brother that was elected after him shold be
           murthered before his coronation, wherupon there is great confusion in
           those parts. And this being all I can bethincke me of for the present I
           will commit you to Gods protection. From London this 4th of May
           1598.
          </p>

        <closer>
          <salute rend="right">Yours most assuredly,</salute>
          <signed rend="right">JOHN CHAMBERLAIN</signed>
        </closer>

        <postscript>
          <address>To my very goode frend Master Dudley Carleton attending on the Lord
          Governor of Ostend geve these..</address>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div type="editor-note">
        <head>Editor's Note</head>
        <p>This letter, dated 4 May 1598, finds John Chamberlain writing from London to Dudley Carleton shortly after returning from Knebworth. The letter offers advice to Carleton on his military prospects and reflects on affairs of state, including diplomatic maneuvers involving France, the Netherlands, and Spain. Chamberlain comments on political instability in Ireland, conspiracies against Queen Elizabeth and the Earl of Essex, and news from Muscovy following the death of the Russian emperor. The letter also records several notable deaths among legal and political figures, as well as local executions and escapes. As in other letters, Chamberlain's tone mixes concern, irony, and close attention to court and foreign affairs.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="notes"/>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>