<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Letter from John Chamberlain to Dudley Carleton, 17 May 1598</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editor</resp>
          <name>Brandon Taylor</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Published digitally at earlymodernletters.org. Licensed under CC BY 4.0.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>The Letters of John Chamberlain</title>
          <editor>Norman Egbert McClure</editor>
          <pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>
          <publisher>American Philosophical Society</publisher>
          <date when="1939">1939</date>
          <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
          <biblScope unit="page">35–37</biblScope>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="letter-meta">
        <head>Letter Metadata</head>
        <p><date when="1598-05-17">17 May 1598</date></p>
        <p><placeName ref="#london">London</placeName></p>
        <p><correspDesc>
          <correspAction type="sent">
            <persName ref="#chamberlain-john">John Chamberlain</persName>
            <date when="1598-05-17"/>
            <placeName ref="#london">London</placeName>
          </correspAction>
          <correspAction type="received">
            <persName ref="#carleton-dudley">Dudley Carleton</persName>
            <placeName ref="#ostend">Ostend</placeName>
          </correspAction>
        </correspDesc></p>
      </div>
    </front>

    <body>
      <div type="letter-text">
        <opener>
          <salute>Goode Master <persName ref="#carleton-dudley">Carleton</persName>,</salute>
        </opener>

        <p>You have gotten the start so far before me, that I am almost out of hope to overtake
        you, and yet I have not bene altogether negligent, for this is my second letter since my
        comming to towne about the beginning of this moneth, but I doubt mine do not finde such
        spedy passage as yours do hitherwards, for I receved one of the 10th upon the 13th of this
        present, and another of the 12th yesterday. I delivered my last at
        <persName ref="#williams-alexander">Master Williams</persName><note place="foot">Presumably
        Alexander Williams.</note> to be sent with the first opportunity, but I understand by
        <persName ref="#carleton-alice">Mistris Alice</persName><note place="foot">Alice
        Carleton.</note> yt was there within these three dayes: this (according to your direction)
        I send by <persName ref="#clarke-edward">Master Clarke</persName><note place="foot">Edward
        Clarke, appointed Clerk of the Council in 1603, and later in the service of George Villiers,
        first Duke of Buckingham.</note>, whom I could not heare of at your
        <persName ref="#norris-edward">Lord Governors</persName><note place="foot">Sir Edward
        Norris, Governor of Ostend, third son of Henry Lord Norris of Rycote.</note>, but I caused
        my man to finde him out in Litle Woodstreet, but (by his sayeng) he made more questions and
        examined him upon more interrogatories then the conveying of a letter comes to, so that yf
        you have any better meanes let me know yt, and I will not fayle you from time to time while
        I am here.</p>

        <p>We are all of opinion that the peace is forward and the
        <persName ref="#sackville-thomas">Lord Buckhurst</persName><note place="foot">Thomas
        Sackville, Lord Buckhurst (created Earl of Dorset, 1604).</note> is appointed to go to
        <placeName ref="#abbeville">Abbeville</placeName> or some other place thereabout to conclude
        yt. <persName ref="#bodley-thomas">Master Bodley</persName><note place="foot">Thomas Bodley
        (knighted, 1604), founder of the Bodleian Library.</note> is named as an assistant, for
        countenance, but he will not go yf he can possiblie avoyde yt. There is speach likewise of
        some greater man goes as the <persName ref="#paulet-william">Lord Marquis of
        Winchester</persName><note place="foot">William Paulet, third Marquis of
        Winchester.</note>, or the <persName ref="#percy-henry">erle of
        Northumberland</persName><note place="foot">Henry Percy, ninth Earl of
        Northumberland.</note> or the <persName ref="#talbot-gilbert">erle of
        Shrewsburie</persName><note place="foot">Gilbert Talbot, seventh Earl of
        Shrewsbury.</note>. Matters in <placeName ref="#ireland">Ireland</placeName> grow dayly
        worse and worse, so that unles they have round and speedy succoures all is like to go to
        wracke; the counsayle have consulted about yt these three or fowre dayes, but I heare of no
        resolution but only that 4000 men shalbe sent at leysure. Here go flienge tales that the
        <persName ref="#clifford-george">erle of Cumberland</persName><note place="foot">George
        Clifford, third Earl of Cumberland, sailed from Portsmouth March 6, 1598. He intercepted no
        treasure ships. (G. C. Williamson, <title level="m">George, Third Earl of
        Cumberland</title>, p. 179.)</note> hath met with fowre carraques bounde for the Indies and
        suncke one of them and taken two, but yt is so diversly and faintly reported that I have no
        great beliefe in yt. We say that the Hollanders have taken a rich ship of treasure comming
        out of <placeName ref="#spain">Spaine</placeName> that past by our loytering sentinells that
        lie about the <placeName ref="#the-downs">Downes</placeName>. The
        <persName ref="#seymour-frances">Countesse of Hartford</persName><note place="foot">Frances,
        daughter of William, first Lord Howard of Effingham, and second wife of Edward Seymour,
        Earl of Hertford, died May 14.</note> is lately dead, and mine old frend Tom Powell whose
        companie I shall much want for my walke in Powles.
        <persName ref="#blount-charles">Sir Charles Blunt</persName> stayed behinde Master Secretary
        in <placeName ref="#france">Fraunce</placeName> about a quarrell he had with a
        <persName ref="#leven-melchior">Dutchman that was knighted at Cales</persName><note
        place="foot">Sir Melchior Leven, knighted by Essex at Cadiz, refused to fight Sir Charles
        Blount in Paris on the ground that the King had forbidden duels. (Salisbury MSS., viii, 168,
        219, 224–231.)</note> that had challenged him; newes came two dayes since that they have met
        and that the Duchman is slaine.</p>

        <p>Our goode frend Master <persName ref="#evers-william">Evers</persName> hath at last left
        <placeName ref="#ireland">Irland</placeName> and came to towne last weeke; within three dayes
        after, his cosen the <persName ref="#evers-ralph">Lord Evers</persName><note place="foot"
        >Ralph, third Lord Evers, Warden of the Middle Marches. In November, 1596, he wrote Lord
        Burghley, and in January, 1598, he wrote to Sir Robert Cecil and again to Lord Burghley to
        complain of the insolence and riotous conduct of the Widdringtons or Woodringtons. On
        January 22 they were summoned to appear before the Privy Council, and a month later they
        reached London. On May 14 the Council wrote the Mayor, Recorder, and Sheriffs of London to
        investigate the "affraye betwixt our very good Lord the Lord Eure and his brother and
        certain of the Woodringtons, gentlemen of the Northe Countrey." (Salisbury MSS., viii, 73;
        Border Papers, 226, 506; A. P. C., xxviii, 279, 328, 443.)</note> and his brother
        <persName ref="#evers-william">Sir William</persName> walking the streets with one page
        after them, were set upon (as they say) by fowre or five of the
        <orgName ref="#witheringtons">Witheringtons</orgName> about a country quarrell, and so
        overlayde that the Lord was hurt in the hande, and Sir William receved divers sore wounds as
        in the hande, in the shoulder, over the face, and quite thorough the body, which he holdes
        out yet being the fift day and I hope will do.</p>

        <p><persName ref="#robinson-henry">Dr. Robinson</persName><note place="foot">Henry
        Robinson, Provost of Queen's College, Oxford, 1581–1598, Bishop of Carlisle,
        1598–1616.</note> of <orgName ref="#queens-college-oxford">Quenes Colledge</orgName> is
        made bishop of <placeName ref="#carlisle">Carlile</placeName>, and I heare that
        <persName ref="#edes-richard">Dr. Edes</persName><note place="foot">Richard Edes, Queen's
        Chaplain and Dean of Worcester.</note> preaching at <placeName ref="#oxford">Oxford</placeName>
        on Sonday last was cleane out and could go no farther, but kepe that to yourself.
        <persName ref="#edmondes-thomas">Master Edmondes</persName><note place="foot">Thomas
        Edmondes (knighted, 1603).</note> is either gon or presently going into
        <placeName ref="#france">Fraunce</placeName> with letters to prepare the way for this peace.
        All that I heare of <persName ref="#mathew-tobie">Tobie Mathew</persName> is that he stayde
        in <placeName ref="#france">Fraunce</placeName> where he fell sicke of the small pockes,
        with younge <persName ref="#throckmorton">Throgmorton</persName><note place="foot">Probably
        a son of Thomas Throckmorton of Coughton.</note>. Your cosen
        <persName ref="#lytton-rowland">Lytton</persName><note place="foot">Rowland
        Lytton.</note> and his lady wilbe in towne this weeke.
        <persName ref="#dormer-michael">Master Dormer</persName><note place="foot">Michael
        Dormer.</note> went hence yesterday again.
        <persName ref="#mildmay-anthony">Sir Ant: Mildmay</persName> went last
        <date when="1598-05-14">Thursday</date> into
        <placeName ref="#northamptonshire">Northamptonshire</placeName><note place="foot">Presumably
        to his house at Apethorpe.</note> but wilbe here within this sevenight; in the mean time he
        bad me remember his commendations to you. Your sister
        <persName ref="#carleton-alice">Alice</persName> hath lien at your brother
        <persName ref="#carleton-william">Williams</persName> in the country ever since
        <date when="1598-04-23">St. Georges day</date>, but I thincke she be now with her lady,
        for so she told me fowre dayes ago when I saw her last.</p>

        <closer>
          <salute>And this being all my store of publike or private newes, with my best wishes I
          bid you farewell.</salute>
          <dateline>From <placeName ref="#london">London</placeName> this
          <date when="1598-05-17">17 of May 1598</date>.</dateline>
          <signed>Yours most assuredly<lb/>
          <persName ref="#chamberlain-john">JOHN CHAMBERLAIN</persName>.</signed>
        </closer>

        <postscript>
          <p><address><addrLine>To my assured goode frend Master
          <persName ref="#carleton-dudley">Edward Dudley Carleton</persName> attending on
          <persName ref="#norris-edward">Sir Edward Norris</persName> Lord Governor of
          <placeName ref="#ostend">Ostend</placeName>.</addrLine></address></p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div type="editor-note">
        <head>Editor's Note</head>
        <p>Written from London on 17 May 1598, this is Chamberlain's third surviving letter to
        Dudley Carleton, who was then serving under Sir Edward Norris, Lord Governor of Ostend. The
        letter opens with domestic logistics — the difficulty of reliable letter delivery between
        London and the Continent, and the role of intermediaries including Master Clarke and Alice
        Carleton — before turning to the larger political scene. Chamberlain reports on
        Anglo-Spanish peace negotiations, noting that Lord Buckhurst has been appointed to travel to
        Abbeville to conclude terms. He also relays the deteriorating situation in Ireland, rumors
        of the Earl of Cumberland's naval exploits in the Atlantic (which, as McClure's note
        confirms, proved unfounded), the death of the Countess of Hartford, and a reported duel
        involving Sir Charles Blount and a Flemish knight in Paris. A violent street assault on Lord
        Evers and Sir William Evers by members of the Witherington family — rooted in a long-running
        northern border feud — occupies the third paragraph. The letter closes with a miscellany of
        social and personal news: a new bishopric for Dr. Robinson, an embarrassing failure by Dr.
        Edes in the Oxford pulpit, the movements of Tobie Mathew (ill in France), Rowland Lytton,
        Michael Dormer, Sir Anthony Mildmay, and the whereabouts of Alice Carleton. The letter
        exemplifies Chamberlain's characteristic mode as London correspondent: swift, observational,
        and indifferent to the boundary between high politics and social gossip.</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
