<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Letter from John Chamberlain to Dudley Carleton, 3 January 1599</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editor</resp>
          <name>Brandon Taylor</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Published digitally at earlymodernletters.org. Licensed under CC BY 4.0.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>The Letters of John Chamberlain</title>
          <editor>Norman Egbert McClure</editor>
          <pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>
          <publisher>American Philosophical Society</publisher>
          <date when="1939">1939</date>
          <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
          <biblScope unit="page">61–62</biblScope>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="letter-meta">
        <head>Letter Metadata</head>
        <p><date when="1599-01-03">3 January 1599</date></p>
        <p><placeName ref="#london">London</placeName></p>
        <p><correspDesc>
          <correspAction type="sent">
            <persName ref="#chamberlain-john">John Chamberlain</persName>
            <date when="1599-01-03"/>
            <placeName ref="#london">London</placeName>
          </correspAction>
          <correspAction type="received">
            <persName ref="#carleton-dudley">Dudley Carleton</persName>
            <placeName ref="#ostend">Ostend</placeName>
          </correspAction>
        </correspDesc></p>
      </div>
    </front>

    <body>
      <div type="letter-text">
        <opener>Goode Master Carleton,</opener>

        <p>I receved your letter of the 18th of the last on Christmas day and had aunswered
          yt sooner yf these holy dayes had affoorded any matter to worke on: only the
          winde is come about againe for
          <placeName ref="#ireland">Ireland</placeName>, and the
          <hi rend="italic">disgusto</hi><note>Italian and Spanish for displeasure, grievance;
          the word carried a courtly and diplomatic register. Chamberlain uses it to name —
          tactfully — the dispute over the cochineal debt that had wrecked Essex's command
          on Sunday night, 17 December 1598. See Letter 13.</note> that made stay of the erles
          going for awhile is sweetned and removed, so that now he prepares with all diligence
          and hath 12000<hi rend="italic">li</hi> delivered him to raise five or sixe hundred
          horse. I cannot come by his particular proportions but as far as I can learne, he is
          not to have hence above 2000 besides the 2000 that are to come out of the
          <placeName ref="#low-countries">Lowe Countries</placeName>, which together with the
          10000 (in name) that are saide to be there alredy must make up his number.<note>The
          total of 14,000 soldiers that had originally been proposed for Essex's Irish command
          (see Letter 12) is now recast: 2,000 fresh troops from England, 2,000 drawn from the
          Low Countries garrisons, and 10,000 nominally already in Ireland — a paper strength
          widely understood to be far below the actual field force available.</note> He is so
          yll satisfied of some that have government there alredy as namely
          <persName ref="#wingfield-thomas">Sir Thomas Maria Wingfield</persName><note>Sir Thomas
          Maria Wingfield, a crown officer in Ireland holding a position of authority over troops
          and supply; one of those knighted by the departing Lord Deputy Sir William Russell in
          May 1597. Essex was dissatisfied with several such incumbent officers and intended to
          replace them wholesale on his arrival.</note> and others, that yt is thought he will
          make a cleane riddaunce and displace most of them.</p>

        <p>Sir
          <persName ref="#norris-thomas">Tho. Norris</persName> hath lately relieved
          <placeName ref="#kilmallock">Killmalloke</placeName><note>Kilmallock, a fortified
          town in County Limerick, was a key English stronghold in Munster and came under
          sustained rebel pressure during the Desmond uprising of 1598–1600. Its relief by
          Norris was one of the few encouraging scraps of Irish news in this period.</note>
          a towne in
          <placeName ref="#munster">Mounster</placeName> that was beset and distressed by the
          enemie: and
          <persName ref="#bagnall-samuel">Sir Samuell Bagnoll</persName> hath don some small
          peece of service upon
          <persName ref="#oneill-hugh">Tiron</persName><note>Tyrone: a synecdoche for Hugh
          O'Neill, second Earl of Tyrone, the principal rebel leader. Chamberlain frequently
          uses the place-name to stand for the man.</note> and brought away three or fowrescore
          cowes. But the rebells are growne so bold that not long since they fetcht away the
          <persName ref="#loftus-adam">Lord Chauncellors</persName><note>Adam Loftus
          (c. 1533–1605), Archbishop of Dublin from 1567 and Lord Chancellor of Ireland from
          1581; the longest-serving royal official in Elizabethan Ireland. That rebels could
          drive off the Lord Chancellor's cattle from his own yard in the shadow of St.
          Patrick's Cathedral — one of the most visible symbols of English Dublin — was a
          measure of how completely the crown had lost control of the countryside.</note>
          cattell out of his yarde close by St. Patricks church in the suburbs of
          <placeName ref="#dublin">Dublin</placeName>, so that yt were more then time the erle
          were there, and yet some doubt he shall hardly get hence before St. Georges
          day.<note>St. George's Day, 23 April, opened the campaigning season. If Essex could
          not embark before then, the summer would be half-spent before any serious military
          action could begin.</note></p>

        <p><persName ref="#mansell-robert">Sir Robert Mansfeld</persName><note>Sir Robert
          Mansell (1573–1656), naval commander; later Vice Admiral of England (1618–1628) and
          a member of the Virginia Company. His three ships were to patrol the Irish Sea and
          interdict rebel communications and supplies by sea.</note> goes shortly with three
          shippes to lie upon that coast. The citie went on reasonable roundly with theyre
          taske and paid in 50000<hi rend="italic">li</hi> the last weeke; the rest is comming
          after, and yt is thought they shalbe excused with as much more or litle
          over.<note>The City of London had been asked to lend £150,000 (see Letters 12 and 13);
          Chamberlain now suggests that paying half — around £50,000 down, with another
          £50,000–£60,000 to follow — will satisfy the crown's immediate need, and that the
          city will be excused from the full amount.</note> Now they are to furnish out 600 men
          for the
          <placeName ref="#low-countries">Lowe Countries</placeName> within these five or sixe
          dayes, but that seemes but a fleabiting after the great blowe.</p>

        <p>The 21 of the last the Quene signed the patents of
          <persName ref="#greville-fulke">Fulke Grivell</persName>,
          <persName ref="#palmer-henry">Sir Henry Palmer</persName>,
          <persName ref="#trevor-john">Trever</persName> (the Lord Admiralls secretarie)
          as Master Treasurer, Controller, and Surveyor of her navie,<note>Fulke Greville
          (1554–1628), poet and statesman, was appointed Treasurer of the Navy on 21 December
          1598, a post he held until 1604. Sir Henry Palmer (c. 1541–1611) became Controller
          of the Navy. John Trevor became Surveyor of the Navy as the Lord Admiral Nottingham's
          secretary. The simultaneous appointment of all three officers on the same day was
          unusual and suggests a deliberate administrative reorganisation of naval
          governance.</note> and the same time yt is saide she cancelled a bond of
          21000<hi rend="italic">li</hi> of the erle of
          <persName ref="#devereux-robert">Essex</persName>, wherin he and a dousen marchants
          were bound for a cochinille.<note>The cancellation of the cochineal bond — or rather
          the partial cancellation of it as a gift — was the settlement of the dispute that had
          blocked Essex's departure in December. See Letter 13: the Queen had promised to forgive
          £12,000 of his father's debt and £20,000 for cochineal, but she had meant only the
          forbearance of it. Now a bond of £21,000 is apparently cancelled outright.</note>
          One
          <persName ref="#browne-peter">Peter Browne</persName><note>Peter Browne, an agent or
          intelligencer caught intercepting diplomatic correspondence. The Gatehouse was a
          prison near Westminster Abbey used for state prisoners and those held at the Council's
          pleasure.</note> is clapt up in the Gatehouse for jugling with the
          <persName ref="#thumery-de-boissise">French ambassadors</persName> letters, who
          complaines that his masters letters and his are usually opened before they come
          at them.</p>

        <p>Yet was expected that the treasurship shold have ben bestowed on the Lord
          <persName ref="#sackville-thomas">Buckhurst</persName> for a new-yeares gift, but yt
          succeded not, so that he must tarry the time, and yt may chaunce light on him on the
          sodain when he doth least looke for yt, according to the custome of the court that
          commonly knowes not over night what shalbe don in the morning. I can bethincke me of
          nothing els, unles yt be the death of
          <persName ref="#owen-thomas">Judge Owen</persName><note>Thomas Owen (d. 1598), judge
          of the Court of Common Pleas. He had been mentioned as a possible Master of the Court
          of Wards — a lucrative post still contested since Lord Burghley's death. His death
          removes one candidate from the running but does nothing to settle the question.</note>
          who was in some speach to be master of the wardes. And so I commit you to God.</p>

        <closer>
          <dateline>From <placeName ref="#london">London</placeName> the
            <date when="1599-01-03">3d of January 1598</date>.</dateline>
          <signed>Yours most assuredly,
            <persName ref="#chamberlain-john">JOHN CHAMBERLAIN</persName>.</signed>
        </closer>

        <postscript>
          <p>To my assured goode frend Master
            <persName ref="#carleton-dudley">Dudley Carleton</persName> attending on the Lord
            Governor of <placeName ref="#ostend">Ostend</placeName> geve these.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
