<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Letter from John Chamberlain to Dudley Carleton, 8 December 1598</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editor</resp>
          <name>Brandon Taylor</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Published digitally at earlymodernletters.org. Licensed under CC BY 4.0.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>The Letters of John Chamberlain</title>
          <editor>Norman Egbert McClure</editor>
          <pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>
          <publisher>American Philosophical Society</publisher>
          <date when="1939">1939</date>
          <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
          <biblScope unit="page">55–57</biblScope>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="letter-meta">
        <head>Letter Metadata</head>
        <p><date when="1598-12-08">8 December 1598</date></p>
        <p><placeName ref="#london">London</placeName></p>
        <p><correspDesc>
          <correspAction type="sent">
            <persName ref="#chamberlain-john">John Chamberlain</persName>
            <date when="1598-12-08"/>
            <placeName ref="#london">London</placeName>
          </correspAction>
          <correspAction type="received">
            <persName ref="#carleton-dudley">Dudley Carleton</persName>
            <placeName ref="#ostend">Ostend</placeName>
          </correspAction>
        </correspDesc></p>
      </div>
    </front>

    <body>
      <div type="letter-text">
        <opener>Goode Master Carleton,</opener>

        <p>I wrote by the post of Sandwich but what meanes yt made to get over I know not. I
          thancke you, but specially for the letter of the 25 of the last, for which your skipper
          brought me yours so full of perticulers which the winter weather affoordes. Here are no
          great novelties for
          <placeName ref="#ireland">Ireland</placeName>, but the whole plot and the erle of
          <persName ref="#devereux-robert">Essex</persName> his jorny thether is neither fast nor
          loose but holdes still in suspence, by reason the proportions thought fit for such an
          enterprise are dayly clipt and deminished; for yt was first set downe that his number
          (with those that be there alredy) shold be 14000 and so to be continued from time to
          time with full allowaunce of vitayle, mony, and other charge aunswerable, but they
          thincke the matter may be compassed with lesse, and on these termes yt standes, wherewith
          he is nothing pleased. For eight or ten dayes the souldiers flockt about him and every
          man hoped to be a colonell at least, and to content theyre humors somwhat yt was said
          there shold be petty regiments raised of 500 and 300 men. The erle of
          <persName ref="#wriothesley-henry">Southampton</persName> was named to be generall of
          the horse,
          <persName ref="#sidney-robert">Sir Rob. Sidney</persName> to be Lord Marshall, and I
          know not how many more to other places; but now all is husht again and only
          <persName ref="#savage-arthur">Sir Arthur Savage</persName><note>Sir Arthur Savage
          (d. 1631), soldier and MP; served in Ireland in various capacities through the Nine
          Years' War. He was among the few officers who actually proceeded to Ireland in late
          1598, ahead of Essex's main expedition the following year.</note> is going thether with
          a thowsand men, and the erle of
          <persName ref="#obrien-donough">Tomond</persName><note>Donough O'Brien (c. 1560–1624),
          fourth Earl of Thomond; one of the few Gaelic-descended Irish magnates who remained
          consistently loyal to the English crown throughout the Nine Years' War. His appointment
          as governor of Limerick gave the English a secure foothold in Munster.</note> with some
          other small forces to governor of
          <placeName ref="#limerick">Limricke</placeName>. Here is order geven for 2000 men to
          be sent out of
          <placeName ref="#kent">Kent</placeName>,
          <placeName ref="#surrey">Surrey</placeName>, and
          <placeName ref="#sussex">Sussex</placeName> into the
          <placeName ref="#low-countries">Lowe Countries</placeName>, and to be drawne from
          thence out of the garrison for
          <placeName ref="#ireland">Ireland</placeName>; and for horsemen to that service the
          justices of peace throughout
          <placeName ref="#england">England</placeName> must be intreated to furnish them.</p>

        <p>But the greatest difficultie is mony, which goes so lowe that for all the subsidies
          comming on, the privy seales that are past,<note>Privy seals were letters under the
          Privy Seal directing wealthy individuals to lend specified sums to the crown —
          effectively a forced loan mechanism. Combined with parliamentary subsidies, they were
          the principal instruments of Elizabethan war finance.</note> and the loane of 20000<hi
          rend="italic">li</hi> the other day, the Quene is now in hand to borrow of the Citie
          150000<hi rend="italic">li</hi>, offering to lay 5000<hi rend="italic">li</hi> of her
          land in morgage, and the customes of the citie of
          <placeName ref="#london">London</placeName> for the repayment of yt, and the
          marchaunts and aldermen of
          <placeName ref="#london">London</placeName> are sent for and dealt with severally and
          urged to lend some 3000<hi rend="italic">li</hi>, some 2000<hi rend="italic">li</hi>,
          some more, some lesse; but howsoever yt fall out, yea though they were willing, I hardly
          thincke yt is to be had, for the citie is much decayed by reason theyre trafike is
          greatly impaired, and the marchant adventurers were almost upon dissolving, being
          hindered in theyre trade by certain enterlopers against whom they could have no remedy.
          Many men muse how the Quene, being discharged of the burthen of the
          <placeName ref="#low-countries">Lowe Countries</placeName>, and having no other charge
          but
          <placeName ref="#ireland">Ireland</placeName>, should be driven to these straights, and
          unles there shold be exceding urgent need indeed, yt is thought a straunge pollicie to
          discover our want so far to the world.<note>Chamberlain's point is a political one:
          public knowledge of the crown's financial straits would encourage England's enemies
          abroad and embolden the Irish rebels. Revealing fiscal weakness was itself a strategic
          liability.</note> The Lord
          <persName ref="#sackville-thomas">Buckhurst</persName> is now in full cry to be Lord
          Treasurer, and yt is thought the wardes<note>The Mastership of the Court of Wards and
          Liveries, the most lucrative royal office available, still contested between Essex and
          others; see Letters 9–11.</note> will fall to
          <persName ref="#cecil-robert">Master Secretary</persName>, yet some say the Quene will
          bestow yt upon some meane man who for a pension shall execute the place to her best
          advantage. Yt was said awhile that the erle of
          <persName ref="#devereux-robert">Essex</persName> should have 6000<hi
          rend="italic">li</hi> yeerely out of yt, otherwhile that he shold have 20000<hi
          rend="italic">li</hi> toward the paiment of his debts and so to leave his hold, but we
          see neither come on very fast. He kept a kinde of marshalls court of late where the
          title of
          <persName ref="#neville-edward">Sir Nevill</persName><note>Edward Neville
          (c. 1556–1618), who claimed the barony of Abergavenny through the female line. The
          hearing concerned whether he was entitled to be summoned to Parliament as Lord
          Abergavenny; he was eventually so summoned in 1604.</note> that claimes to be Lord of
          Aberge<supplied>n</supplied>y, and the title of
          <persName ref="#leonard-henry">Sir Henry Leonard</persName><note>Sir Henry Leonard
          (d. 1626), son of Sampson Leonard and Margaret, suo jure Baroness Dacre. His claim to
          the barony of Dacre of the South was ultimately resolved in his favour; he succeeded
          as twelfth Lord Dacre in 1612.</note> that wold be Lord Dacres of the South was
          argued, but after divers hearings he left the matter as he found yt, and so yt is
          referred to the Quene.</p>

        <p>We heare that
          <persName ref="#sherley-anthony">Sir Ant. Sherley</persName><note>Sir Anthony Sherley
          (1565–1636?), adventurer and self-styled diplomat. He had set out for Persia in 1598
          on an unauthorised mission to the Shah, passing through the Ottoman Empire and the
          Levant. At Constantinople and Aleppo he extorted money from English merchants by
          issuing bills of exchange drawn on Essex — without any authorisation to do so. His
          subsequent wanderings made him notorious across Europe.</note> hath ben at
          <placeName ref="#constantinople">Constantinople</placeName> and there wrounge out of our
          marchants 400<hi rend="italic">li</hi>, and from thence he went to
          <placeName ref="#aleppo">Aleppo</placeName> and there scraped together 500<hi
          rend="italic">li</hi> more, wherewith he hath charged billes by the Lord of
          <persName ref="#devereux-robert">Essex</persName> his name, and so is gon on God
          knowes whether to seeke his fortune.
          <persName ref="#leveson-richard">Sir Richard Lewson</persName><note>Sir Richard Leveson
          (c. 1570–1605), naval commander; son of Sir Walter Leveson of Lilleshall, Shropshire.
          He distinguished himself in later actions against Spanish shipping and became Vice
          Admiral of England in 1604.</note> hath lately staide 17 saile of Easterlings and
          Hollanders in the narrow seas that were going for
          <placeName ref="#spain">Spaine</placeName>; in the mean time his father<note>Sir Walter
          Leveson of Lilleshall, Shropshire; detained in the Fleet prison by creditors who had
          laid a trap for him and caught him at Lambeth.</note> is staide in the Fleet, being
          faln into hucksters handes (I mean his old creditors) who laide a traine for him and
          caught him at Lambeth. The <persName ref="#paulet-william">Lord Marquis</persName><note>William Paulet (c. 1532–1598), third
          Marquis of Winchester. He died on 25 November 1598 and was succeeded by his son
          William, fourth Marquis.</note> is lately dead having left a noble sonne to succeed
          him, who is like to prove as sufficient a man as none of them all.
          <persName ref="#parker-edward">Master Parker</persName><note>A brother of Edward Parker,
          tenth Lord Morley (1550–1618). The slain man's given name is not recorded.</note>
          brother to the
          <persName ref="#morley-edward">Lord Morley</persName> was slaine the last weeke by a
          man of Sir Tho. Gerrards about a brabble the way, wherof the fellow is acquitted, being
          found he did yt in his owne defence.</p>

        <p>The French inventairie<note><hi rend="italic">Inventaire Général de l'Histoire de
          France</hi> (Paris, 1597) by Jean de Serres (c. 1540–1598), a comprehensive history of
          France; the author died before completing the work.</note> is not come foorth, the
          author being saide to be dead, but there is hope yt wilbe found among his papers. Here
          is nothing come out this last mart<note>The Frankfurt book fair (Buchmesse), held twice
          yearly and the main international book market. Chamberlain regularly reported on what
          was available at Frankfurt to Carleton, who collected books.</note> worth the looking
          after; for that many thinges are currant there that be here forbidden, I send you likewise
          such pedlarie pamflets and threehalfpeny ware as we are served with, and I do not thincke
          but you may fit yourself better at Middleburg, but make the best use you can of them and
          use your owne censure; but yf I be not deceved some of the satires are passable. You
          shall receve by this bearer your
          <persName ref="#ortelius-abraham">Ortelius</persName> his <hi rend="italic">Thesaurus
          Geographicus</hi>,<note>Finally dispatched after being held up since Letter 10, when
          it was judged too large for ordinary post. It is sent by a special bearer, with
          <persName ref="#lytton-rowland">Rowland Lytton</persName> insisting on paying for
          it.</note> your cousen Lytton will needs bestow yt on you, wherin I made no longe
          strife. Our
          <persName ref="#lytton-anne">Mistris Anne</persName><note>Anne Lytton, probably a
          daughter or close relation of Rowland Lytton of Knebworth. An old doctor of law who had
          long kept her in expectation of marriage died without fulfilling his promise, leaving
          her a widow before she was a wife.</note> is become a widow before she was a wife, an
          old Doctor of Law that hath held her long in hand to marry her being dead, whereupon
          she mournes in her chamber. And
          <persName ref="#sherley-george">Master Sherley</persName><note>George Shirley
          (c. 1559–1622), an acquaintance of Chamberlain's and Carleton's circles; previously
          mentioned in Letter 5.</note> hath at last married the
          <persName ref="#unton-dorothy">Lady Umpton</persName><note>Dorothy Unton (née
          Wroughton; d. 1634), widow of Sir Henry Unton (1558–1596), the diplomat and subject
          of the celebrated memorial portrait now in the National Portrait Gallery. Chamberlain's
          sardonic remark — that "as poor a man as I am I would not buy such another of the
          price" — implies Lady Unton had a reputation for being difficult.</note> and made her
          his deere wife; for mine owne part as poore a man as I am I wold not buy such another
          of the price.
          <persName ref="#perkins-christopher">Doctor Parkins</persName> is come out of
          <placeName ref="#denmark">Denmarke</placeName>, and sayes he hath brought a goode
          aunswer. And thus wishing you all health and welfare I end for this time.</p>

        <closer>
          <dateline>From <placeName ref="#london">London</placeName> this
            <date when="1598-12-08">8th of December 1598</date>.</dateline>
          <signed>Yours most assuredly,
            <persName ref="#chamberlain-john">JOHN CHAMBERLAIN</persName>.</signed>
        </closer>

        <postscript>
          <p>To my very goode frend Master
            <persName ref="#carleton-dudley">Dudley Carleton</persName> attending on the Lord
            Governor of <placeName ref="#ostend">Ostend</placeName> geve these.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
