<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Letter 1 – Financial Concerns, Court Gossip, and the Islands Voyage</title>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Brandon Taylor</name>
          <resp>Editor and Verifier</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Early Modern Letters Project</publisher>
        <idno type="uri">https://earlymodernletters.org/letters/chamberlain-letter1.xml</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <idno type="series">P. Dom.</idno>
          <idno type="collection">Elm.</idno>
          <idno type="shelfmark">ccIx'm</idno>
          <note>pp.</note>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <correspDesc>
        <correspAction type="sent">
          <persName ref="#chamberlain-john">John Chamberlain</persName>
          <placeName ref="#london">London</placeName>
          <date when="1597-06-11"/>
        </correspAction>
        <correspAction type="received">
          <persName ref="#carleton-dudley">Dudley Carleton</persName>
          <placeName ref="#paris">Paris</placeName>
        </correspAction>
      </correspDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="letter-meta">
        <head>Letter 1 – Financial Concerns, Court Gossip, and the Islands Voyage</head>
        <p><date when="1597-06-11">June 11, 1597</date></p>
        <p><placeName ref="#london">London</placeName></p>
        <!-- correspDesc moved to teiHeader/profileDesc -->
      </div>
    </front>

    <body>
      <div type="letter-text">
        <opener>
          <salute>Goode Master Carleton,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p>I know you looked long ere this to have heard from me, and so might you well have done, if Painter the post had not kept your letter of the eighth of May <note>The reference is to an earlier letter from Carleton delayed by the post.</note> till the sixth of this present June.</p>

        <p>I received a little billet before, by your sister Williams, <note>Elizabeth, wife of Alexander Williams.</note> in the way of an interim till you had better leisure, but presently upon it went to Askot <note>Ascott, Oxfordshire, home of Michael Dormer (knighted, 1604).</note> where I met with your brother Carleton <note>George Carleton of Huntercombe.</note> (coming from the burial of your uncle Goodwin <note>Son of John Goodwin and Carleton’s maternal uncle.</note>), who told me Tobie Mathew <note>Later Archbishop of York.</note> had showed him a letter from you wherein you complained much of want, and what narrow straits you were likely to be driven to.</p>

        <p>Whereupon I gathered that his intention was to move me in your behalf, as indeed it was, and I was glad of it, as a good occasion, both to show my love to you, and to satisfy myself in that I have so long owed you; so that if you may be content to have so little, you shall not utterly want, as long as I have.</p>

        <p>But I pray you, consider how much better it were for you to make the trial to your parents, who are much more bound to you, and better able than I am, for I confess it will go hard with me to perform what I promise.</p>

        <p>From London this longest day of 1597.</p>

        <p>I was last week at a christening of Lady Umpton’s daughter, <note>Possibly related to the family of Edward Uvedale, a minor gentry line in Berkshire.</note> where <persName ref="#shirley-george" cert="medium">George Shirley</persName> and others met and made good cheer, but with such riotous disorder that I was sorry I came among them.</p>

        <seg type="topic" n="Court and Drama">
          <p>There was a captain called Woodward, <note>Captain Woodward was punished in Star Chamber for circulating seditious pamphlets criticizing court policy.</note> condemned in Star Chamber for a seditious pamphlet; and one of the players punished about a matter in a new play called Humors, <note type="editorial">Likely a reference to George Chapman's <hi rend="italic">An Humorous Day’s Mirth</hi> (1597).</note> which I suppose you have heard of.</p>
        </seg>

        <seg type="topic" n="Naval Affairs">
          <p>We look daily for news of the success of the Islands Voyage. <note type="editorial">A failed 1597 naval expedition led by Essex and Raleigh against Spanish ports in the Azores.</note> Sir Francis Drake’s letters have not been very welcome to court, for he taxed some of the council with slackness or backwardness. <note type="editorial">Drake’s reports were seen as politically pointed, criticizing the Privy Council’s indecision.</note></p>
        </seg>

        <p>I mean to go for Ireland within a fortnight, if no occasion prevent me, where I hope to do some service and make good my promises.</p>

        <p>Your sister is well, and she and your cousin are both diligent in remembrance of you. I have not seen your friend in Gray’s Inn lately.</p>

        <p>I commend me most heartily to Sir Thomas Edmondes, <note>Edmondes was then serving as English envoy to the French court.</note> whose letters have always been very welcome. I hope he continues to prosper in his employment and to deserve the favor he enjoys.</p>

        <p>This letter I make bold to commend to Sir Thomas’s dispatch, not doubting of his care and diligence in seeing it safely delivered.</p>

        <p>And so I bid you farewell, wishing you all happiness and advancement.</p>

        <closer>
          <salute rend="right">Yours most assuredly,</salute>
          <signed rend="right">JOHN CHAMBERLAIN</signed>
        </closer>

        <postscript>
          <address>To my assured good frend Master Dudley Carleton attendaunt on the Lord Ambassador for her Majestie at Paris.</address>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div type="editor-note">
        <head>Editor's Note</head>
        <p>This letter offers a vivid window into Chamberlain’s early correspondence with Dudley Carleton. It touches on military news from Ireland, preparations for the “Islands Voyage,” court gossip, and Chamberlain’s own pending journey. Notable are Chamberlain’s indirect counsel to Carleton regarding financial support, and his detailed intelligence-gathering style. This letter also signals Chamberlain’s early tendency to function as a political informant and social interpreter.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="notes"/>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
