<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Letter from John Chamberlain to Dudley Carleton, 20 October 1598</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editor</resp>
          <name>Brandon Taylor</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Published digitally at earlymodernletters.org. Licensed under CC BY 4.0.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>The Letters of John Chamberlain</title>
          <editor>Norman Egbert McClure</editor>
          <pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>
          <publisher>American Philosophical Society</publisher>
          <date when="1939">1939</date>
          <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
          <biblScope unit="page">48–50</biblScope>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="letter-meta">
        <head>Letter Metadata</head>
        <p><date when="1598-10-20">20 October 1598</date></p>
        <p><placeName ref="#london">London</placeName></p>
        <p><correspDesc>
          <correspAction type="sent">
            <persName ref="#chamberlain-john">John Chamberlain</persName>
            <date when="1598-10-20"/>
            <placeName ref="#london">London</placeName>
          </correspAction>
          <correspAction type="received">
            <persName ref="#carleton-dudley">Dudley Carleton</persName>
            <placeName ref="#ostend">Ostend</placeName>
          </correspAction>
        </correspDesc></p>
      </div>
    </front>

    <body>
      <div type="letter-text">
        <opener>Master Carleton,</opener>

        <p>I wrote to you about the third or fourth of this present, and have now staide the longer
          to see yf this northeasterly wind wold have brought us any thing from you, or brought
          foorth any thing at home worth the sending: but we are still at the same stay as when I
          wrote you last and we are fed on from Sonday to Sonday with expectation from the court,
          wherewith I am so weary that I will not tarry nor trifle out the time any longer, but
          acquaint you with matters as they stand now, though yt be certainly thought we shall have
          some alteration on Sonday next.</p>

        <p>The voyce ran all this weeke with
          <persName ref="#fortescue-john">Sir John Fortescue</persName><note>Chancellor of the
          Exchequer. The contest for Lord Treasurer eventually settled on
          <persName ref="#sackville-thomas">Lord Buckhurst</persName>, who was appointed in May
          1599.</note> to be Lord Treasurer, but now yt is come about again to the
          <persName ref="#sackville-thomas">Lord Buckhurst</persName>,<note>Thomas Sackville,
          Lord Buckhurst, later first Earl of Dorset (1604). He was appointed Lord Treasurer in
          May 1599 and held the office until his death in 1608.</note> and so every three or fowre
          dayes yt is tossed from the one side of the court to the other. The next new counsaillors
          are thought shalbe the
          <persName ref="#blount-charles">Lord Mountjoye</persName> and the
          <persName ref="#popham-john">Lord Cheife Justice</persName>,<note>Sir John Popham
          (c. 1531–1607), Lord Chief Justice since 1592. Chamberlain's remark about his haunting
          of whorehouses while persecuting prostitutes was a common piece of London gossip;
          Popham's moralistic severity on the bench was widely noted.</note> who hath plaide rex
          of late among whoores and bawdes and persecutes poore pretty wenches out of all pittie
          and mercy. The court of wardes sitts still not for want of a master, and though the earle
          of <persName ref="#devereux-robert">Essex</persName> be alone in election yet there is
          still some rub in his way that he comes not on. Some say the Quene meanes to dissolve
          that court and in stead therof to raise a yearely contribution out of all landes in capite
          or knight service, which wold be more for her profit and lesse grevance to the subject,
          but that is too goode to be true. Others say he may have yt yf he will, but because there
          is a course spoken of somwhat to geld and curtall yt he refuseth to accept yt unles he may
          have yt whole and unmaimed. And others say he findes some scruple in the strictnes of the
          othe, and wonders how the
          <persName ref="#cecil-william">late Lord Treasurer</persName><note>William Cecil, Lord
          Burghley (1520–1598), who died 4 August 1598. See Letter 6.</note> could dispense so
          easilie and so largely with yt and his conscience: but this were somwhat too pure and
          maidenlike or rather <hi rend="italic">inutilis verecundia</hi>.</p>

        <p>The state of
          <placeName ref="#ireland">Ireland</placeName> growes dayly <hi rend="italic">di mal in
          peggio</hi>, for they begin now to stirre in the province of
          <placeName ref="#munster">Munster</placeName>, where the
          <persName ref="#fitzgibbon-edmund">white knight</persName>,<note>Edmund Fitzgibbon
          (d. c. 1600), hereditary White Knight of County Cork, a title held in the Fitzgibbon
          family. He supported the Munster rebellion during the Nine Years' War.</note>
          <persName ref="#fitzgerald-james">Sir James of Desmond</persName><note>James Fitzthomas
          Fitzgerald (d. 1607), grandson of the fourteenth Earl of Desmond. In 1598 he assumed
          the title of Earl of Desmond and put himself at the head of a force of approximately
          8,000 clansmen. (<hi rend="italic">Cal. S. P. Ireland</hi>, 1598–1599, p. 499.)</note>
          and one <persName ref="#condon-patrick">Patricke Condon</persName> a shrewd fellow are
          out. <persName ref="#bagnall-samuel">Sir Samuell Bagnoll</persName> is there beinge
          lately stabd by
          <persName ref="#st-lawrence-christopher">St. Laurence</persName> (sonne and heire to
          the <persName ref="#st-lawrence-nicholas">Lord of Hooth</persName>) about the lie or
          such like brabble. Some thincke the
          <persName ref="#blount-charles">Lord Mountjoy</persName> shalbe sent thether deputie;
          others say the earle of
          <persName ref="#devereux-robert">Essex</persName> meanes to take yt upon him, and hopes
          by his countenance that after a yeare he might return a lidger; Mary he wold have yt
          under the brode seale of
          <placeName ref="#england">England</placeName> when he will. Here is a
          <persName ref="#thumery-de-boissise">French ambassador</persName><note>Le Sieur Thumery
          de Boissise, who landed at Dover on 14 October 1598 and remained as French ambassador
          in England until 1601.</note> (a civilian) rather sent at the earnest request of the
          Frenchmen for any great love or busines of theyre owne; others say his cheife errand is
          about matters of piracie, wherof the Frenchmen complaine excedingly.</p>

        <p>Here is some speach of sending
          <persName ref="#herbert-john">Dr. Harbert</persName>,
          <persName ref="#parry-thomas">Sir Thomas Parri</persName>,
          <persName ref="#bodley-thomas">Master Bodley</persName>, and
          <persName ref="#neville-henry">Master Nevill</persName> of
          <placeName ref="#berkshire">Berkshire</placeName> in question [for an embassy to
          <placeName ref="#france">France</placeName>]: besides that somebody must be sent
          extraordinarie to the marriage of Madame the Kings sister wherto
          <persName ref="#sidney-robert">Sir Robert Sidney</persName> is most named.
          <persName ref="#wroth-john">John Wroth</persName> is making redy to go ambassador into
          <placeName ref="#turkey">Turkie</placeName>.
          <persName ref="#vere-francis">Sir Fra: Vere</persName> is comming to the
          <placeName ref="#brill">Brill</placeName> out of which intertainment he paies yearly
          400<hi rend="italic">li</hi> to the
          <persName ref="#burroughs-lady">Lady Borroughs</persName>.<note>Frances, widow of
          Thomas, fifth Lord Burgh (d. 1597), who had governed the Brill before Vere. See
          Letter 8.</note> There was some snapping of late twixt him and the
          <persName ref="#grey-thomas-wilton">young Lord Gray</persName><note>Thomas Grey,
          fifteenth Baron Grey of Wilton (1575–1614), later condemned for his role in the
          Bye Plot (1603) and kept in the Tower until his death.</note> who went about to have a
          regiment and to be cheife commander over the English in the
          <placeName ref="#low-countries">Lowe Countries</placeName>.
          <persName ref="#gilbert-john">Sir John Gilbert</persName><note>Elder brother of Sir
          Humphrey Gilbert and half-brother of Sir Walter Raleigh. See Letter 8.</note> with six
          or seven sayle one and other is going for
          <placeName ref="#guiana">Guiana</placeName>. I heare that
          <persName ref="#raleigh-walter">Sir Walter Raleigh</persName> shold be so deeply
          discontented, and almost that he is not far from making a voyage that way himself.</p>

        <p>Fowre or five more of
          <persName ref="#stanley-john">Stanlies</persName> consorts are lately apprehended and
          sent to the Towre, among whom are one Rolles, Pates, and
          <persName ref="#bagshaw-christopher">Dr. Bagshaw</persName>.<note>Christopher Bagshaw
          (c. 1552–1625), Catholic priest and controversialist. His arrest with Stanley's
          associates reflects the government's vigilance against suspected Catholic agents in
          autumn 1598.</note> The
          <persName ref="#sigismund-iii">king of Poland</persName><note>Sigismund III Vasa
          (1566–1632), King of Poland-Lithuania and hereditary claimant to the Swedish throne.
          His Protestant uncle Charles of Södermanland had effectively seized control of Sweden
          by 1598 and would be crowned Charles IX in 1604.</note> is saide to be in hard termes
          taken in <placeName ref="#sweden">Sweden</placeName> by his uncle the
          <persName ref="#charles-ix-sweden">Duke Charles</persName>. There is one at
          <placeName ref="#venice">Venice</placeName> geves himself out to be
          <persName ref="#sebastian-portugal">Sebastian</persName> the late king of
          <placeName ref="#portugal">Portingale</placeName>, and sayes he was not slaine<note>
          Sebastian I of Portugal was widely believed killed at the battle of Alcáçar Quibir in
          Morocco in 1578. A string of pretenders claiming to be the lost king appeared in the
          following decades; this unnamed individual at Venice was one of several.</note> at the
          battell in Barberie (as was thought) but taken prisoner, and concealed himself till he
          might conveniently get away. They make him aunswer that if he be the man, he shall not
          want maintenaunce nor theyre mediation, but yf he be not, he must look for that he
          deserves. We say the younge
          <persName ref="#philip-iii">kinde of Spaine</persName><note>Philip III (1578–1621),
          who had succeeded his father Philip II in September 1598.</note> hath either of her
          owne motion or by his order keepes the
          <persName ref="#isabella-clara">Infanta</persName> in a monasterie of nunnes till the
          <persName ref="#albert-archduke">archduke</persName> come to fetch her.</p>

        <p>We thincke me of nothing ells unles I should tell you of certain mad knaves that tooke
          Tabacco all the way to
          <placeName ref="#tyburn">Tiborn</placeName> as they went to hanging. I have here sent
          you some verses that go under the name of my Lord of
          <persName ref="#devereux-robert">Essex</persName> when he was in disgrace, but I cannot
          warrant them to be his nor made at that time.<note>The enclosure is not extant. Several
          lyrics have been attributed to Essex, possibly composed during his retirement at Wanstead
          in 1598; Chamberlain may have sent the lyric beginning "Happy were he could finish forth
          his fate / In some unhaunted desert." (Ault, <hi rend="italic">Elizabethan Lyrics</hi>,
          p. 270.)</note> Your cousin
          <persName ref="#lytton-rowland">Lytton</persName> was here two dayes at the beginning
          of the weeke, but is gon downe to the buriall of
          <persName ref="#brockett-john">Sir John Brocket</persName>. I have not heard lately of
          your brother nor of any other of your frends, so that with a short
          <hi rend="italic">bezo las manos</hi> I bid you farewell for this time.</p>

        <closer>
          <dateline>From <placeName ref="#london">London</placeName> this
            <date when="1598-10-20">20th of October 1598</date>.</dateline>
          <signed>Yours most assuredly,
            <persName ref="#chamberlain-john">JOHN CHAMBERLAIN</persName>.</signed>
        </closer>

        <postscript>
          <p>To my assured goode frend Master
            <persName ref="#carleton-dudley">Dudley Carleton</persName> attending on the Lord
            Governor of <placeName ref="#ostend">Ostend</placeName> geve these.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div type="editor-note">
        <head>Editor's Note</head>
        <p>Written from London three weeks after Letter 8, this letter surveys a wide panorama of
          news in the autumn of 1598. The court is still deadlocked over the succession to Lord
          Burghley's offices: the Lord Treasurer's post oscillates between Sir John Fortescue and
          Lord Buckhurst, while Essex's long-expected mastership of the Court of Wards remains
          out of reach — stalled variously by the Queen's reform proposals, Essex's own
          intransigence, and a reported scruple about the master's oath. Ireland dominates the
          middle of the letter: Munster is rising, with a Fitzgerald claimant to the earldom of
          Desmond and the White Knight in the field, and both Mountjoy and Essex are floated as
          candidates for the Lord Deputyship. Woven among these urgent matters is a brisk catalogue
          of diplomatic activity: a newly arrived French ambassador, several names in the running
          for an embassy to Paris, Vere's quarrel with young Lord Grey over the Brill command,
          Stanley's arrested confederates, and Raleigh sulking toward another Guiana venture. The
          letter closes with sardonic asides about condemned men smoking tobacco on the way to
          Tyburn, and a note of unease about some verses circulating under Essex's name that
          Chamberlain cannot quite vouch for.</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
