<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Letter from John Chamberlain to Dudley Carleton, 3 October 1598</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editor</resp>
          <name>Brandon Taylor</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Published digitally at earlymodernletters.org. Licensed under CC BY 4.0.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>The Letters of John Chamberlain</title>
          <editor>Norman Egbert McClure</editor>
          <pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>
          <publisher>American Philosophical Society</publisher>
          <date when="1939">1939</date>
          <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
          <biblScope unit="page">46–48</biblScope>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="letter-meta">
        <head>Letter Metadata</head>
        <p><date when="1598-10-03">3 October 1598</date></p>
        <p><placeName ref="#london">London</placeName></p>
        <p><correspDesc>
          <correspAction type="sent">
            <persName ref="#chamberlain-john">John Chamberlain</persName>
            <date when="1598-10-03"/>
            <placeName ref="#london">London</placeName>
          </correspAction>
          <correspAction type="received">
            <persName ref="#carleton-dudley">Dudley Carleton</persName>
            <placeName ref="#ostend">Ostend</placeName>
          </correspAction>
        </correspDesc></p>
      </div>
    </front>

    <body>
      <div type="letter-text">
        <opener>Goode Master Carleton,</opener>

        <p>I receved two letters from you at
          <placeName ref="#knebworth">Knebworth</placeName>; to the former I made aunswer from
          thence by a man of
          <persName ref="#harvey-gerrard">Sir Gerrard Harvies</persName>, and now (being called
          hither by some occasion sooner then I looked for), I wold fain requite your kindnes, and
          repay you in the same coine yf our market did affoord yt, but the odds runs too much on
          your side, and the fertilitie of that soyle seemes to flourish with a later springe of
          pamflets and discourses as ever we are here in the dead of winter.</p>

        <p>The erle of
          <persName ref="#devereux-robert">Essex</persName> is at court in as goode termes (they
          say) as ever he was, but there be no offices bestowed nor no more shew of bestowing them
          then the first day the Lord Treasurer died: all men give him theyre voyces to be master
          of the wardes and yt is thought that <hi rend="italic">serius ocyus</hi> yt will light
          upon him. Here hath ben much speach of new counsaillors and some have ben very neere yt
          and appointed to be sworne: but the contrarietie of opinions, the number that stand for
          yt, and the difficultie or rather impossibilitie to please both sides, kepes all backe.
          Yet yt is certainly thought that
          <persName ref="#stanhope-john">Sir John Stanhop</persName><note>During the illness of
          the Lord Chamberlain,
          <persName ref="#carey-george">George Carey, second Lord Hunsdon</persName>, a
          Vice-Chamberlain was needed. Raleigh sought the post, but
          <persName ref="#stanhope-john">Stanhope</persName> was appointed in February
          1601.</note> shalbe shortly vice-chamberlain.
          <persName ref="#vere-francis">Sir Fra: Vere</persName> <hi rend="italic">per tot
          discrimina</hi> and with much heave and shove hath got the government of the
          <placeName ref="#brill">Brill</placeName>. One
          <persName ref="#stanley-john">Stanly</persName><note><persName ref="#stanley-john">John
          Stanley</persName> declared that he had been employed by the King of Spain to kill
          <persName ref="#elizabeth-i">Queen Elizabeth</persName>. (<hi rend="italic">Cal. S. P.
          Dom.</hi>, 1598–1601, pp. 106–107.)</note> that came in sixteen dayes over-land with
          letters out of Spaine, is lately committed to the Towre. He was very ernest to have
          private conference with her Majestie pretending matter of great importaunce which he wold
          by no meanes utter to any body els. He affirmes that the
          <persName ref="#philip-ii">King of Spaine</persName> was not dead at his comming away
          but that he had retired himself and was drawing on. There hath ben some small bickering
          of late in Ireland wherin there were sevenscore rebells slaine (but not of the maine
          troupes of
          <persName ref="#oneill-hugh">Tiron</persName>) yet the newes is very welcome and we are
          glad to make much of a litle. The erle of
          <persName ref="#clifford-george">Cumberland</persName><note>Cf. Letter 2. Camden, in
          his account of the voyage, remarks that he "brought home more victory than booty."
          (<hi rend="italic">Annales</hi>, pp. 497–498. Cf. <hi rend="italic">Purchas</hi>,
          xvi, 29.)</note> is come and some of his shipping; the rest are saide (or rather
          thought) to be upon the coast, for according to our custome they came scattering, and
          every man made shift for himself as though they had plaide at formost take up
          hindmost.</p>

        <p>They had goode hap to misse the Spaniards that lay for them with 30 men of warre at the
          <placeName ref="#terceiras">Terceras</placeName>, and removed from the yland of
          <placeName ref="#flores">Flores</placeName> but the day before the erle came thether.
          The great expectation of this viage is come to this, that they tooke the towne and
          castell of
          <placeName ref="#puerto-rico">Porto-ricco</placeName> where they found no great riches,
          for having intelligence of theyre comming the Spaniards had conveyed away theyre cheife
          wealth. My Lord himself saith that he hath made a saving jorny, but they that understand
          yt better, say that all he hath brought (wherof the greatest part is sugar and ginger)
          will not amount to above fifteen or sixteen thowsand pound, which is not halfe the charge
          of the setting out, besides the adventure and waste of the shipping and the losse of 600
          men, what by sword and sicknes. Some finde great fault and say his owne wilfullnes and
          want of direction overthrew the viage, and that yf he wold have ben advised he might have
          don them all goode, but he neglected present profit in hope of greater matters, and so
          forsooke the substaunce for the shadow. I thincke the heat of our sea viages is well
          alayed by this and the rest, which being no better conducted serve rather to fortefie and
          confirme, then hinder the ennemie.</p>

        <p>I can send you nothing of your private frends for I have neither seen nor heard of any
          of them. I am here all alone till the terme come that we may be <hi rend="italic">plena
          curia</hi>. The court is at
          <placeName ref="#nonsuch">Nonesuch</placeName> and shold come to
          <placeName ref="#richmond">Richmond</placeName> on Tewsday next; yf yt bringe any thinge
          worth the writing I will not fayle you: and so God kepe you.</p>

        <closer>
          <dateline><placeName ref="#london">London</placeName> this
            <date when="1598-10-03">third of October 1598</date>.</dateline>
          <signed>Yours most assuredly,
            <persName ref="#chamberlain-john">JOHN CHAMBERLAIN</persName>.</signed>
        </closer>

        <postscript>
          <p>To my very goode frend Master
            <persName ref="#carleton-dudley">Dudley Carleton</persName> attending on the Lord
            Governor of <placeName ref="#ostend">Ostend</placeName> geve these.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div type="editor-note">
        <head>Editor's Note</head>
        <p>Written shortly after Chamberlain's return to London from Knebworth, this letter
          focuses on two major stories of autumn 1598: the stalled succession struggle following
          Lord Burghley's death and the deeply disappointing outcome of the Earl of Cumberland's
          Caribbean voyage. Essex is back at court but getting no offices; Stanhope is expected as
          Vice-Chamberlain; Vere has finally secured the governorship of the Brill after much
          difficulty. Most alarming is the arrest of one Stanley, who claims he was sent by Spain
          to assassinate the Queen—and who insists Philip II is not yet dead. The bulk of the
          letter, however, concerns Cumberland: his fleet straggled home, the Puerto Rico
          expedition yielded almost nothing of value, and losses in men and shipping far exceeded
          any gains. Chamberlain is characteristically sardonic, concluding that England's appetite
          for sea ventures has surely been cooled by this and similar misadventures.</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
