<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Letter from John Chamberlain to Dudley Carleton, 30 August 1598</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editor</resp>
          <name>Brandon Taylor</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Published digitally at earlymodernletters.org. Licensed under CC BY 4.0.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>The Letters of John Chamberlain</title>
          <editor>Norman Egbert McClure</editor>
          <pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>
          <publisher>American Philosophical Society</publisher>
          <date when="1939">1939</date>
          <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
          <biblScope unit="page">41–45</biblScope>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="letter-meta">
        <head>Letter Metadata</head>
        <p><date when="1598-08-30">30 August 1598</date></p>
        <p><placeName ref="#london">London</placeName></p>
        <p><correspDesc>
          <correspAction type="sent">
            <persName ref="#chamberlain-john">John Chamberlain</persName>
            <date when="1598-08-30"/>
            <placeName ref="#london">London</placeName>
          </correspAction>
          <correspAction type="received">
            <persName ref="#carleton-dudley">Dudley Carleton</persName>
            <placeName ref="#ostend">Ostend</placeName>
          </correspAction>
        </correspDesc></p>
      </div>
    </front>

    <body>
      <div type="letter-text">

        <p>I came out of <placeName ref="#oxfordshire">Oxfordshire</placeName>
        with your cousen <persName ref="#lytton-rowland">Lytton</persName><note>Rowland
        Lytton.</note> posting to <placeName ref="#london">London</placeName>
        on Satterday last, and on Monday came to be a beholder of the solemne
        funerall,<note>Of <persName ref="#cecil-william">William Cecil, Lord
        Burghley</persName>, who died August 4.</note> wherin he and your
        brother <persName ref="#carleton-george">Carleton</persName><note>George
        Carleton.</note> were actors. They are gon downe together this day
        since dinner and have left me to convay theyre letters and to write you
        such refuse newes as peradventure might scape them. But the worst is I
        heare your boat goes away the next tide, so that I am forced to make
        hudling haste which of all things I love not, and that causes me to
        tarry behind them for two or three dayes, for I am no frend to sodain
        motions, but of a setled constitution and naturally loth to remove.</p>

        <p>The Lord Treasurers funerall was performed yesterday with all the
        rites that belonge to so great a personage. The number of mourners one
        and other were above 500 wherof there were many noble men and among the
        rest the <persName ref="#devereux-robert">erle of Essex</persName>, who
        (whether yt were upon consideration of the present occasion, or for his
        owne disfavours) me thought carried the heaviest countenaunce of the
        companie: presently after dinner he retired to
        <placeName ref="#wanstead">Wansted</placeName> where they say he meanes
        to settle, seing he cannot be receved in court, though he have relented
        and sought by divers meanes to recover much and to recover his hold: but
        the Quene sayes he hath playde long enough upon her, and that she meanes
        to play a while upon him, and to stand as much upon her greatnes as he
        hath don upon his stomacke. The Lord Treasurer<note>William Cecil, first
        Baron Burghley (1520–1598), Lord High Treasurer since 1572.</note> hath
        left the Quenes cofers so bare that there is but 20000 to be found, and
        the Quene is faine to demaund in lone of the citie 40000 wherof they can
        presently furnish her but with the one halfe. Of his private wealth there
        is but 11000 come to light and that all in silver: whereof 6000 (with
        eight or nine hundred pound land) he bequeathed to his two neeces of
        <persName ref="#vere-edward">Oxford</persName>,<note>His granddaughters:
        his daughter Anne, wife of Edward Vere, seventeenth Earl of Oxford, had
        three daughters living in 1598 — Elizabeth, wife of William Stanley,
        sixth Earl of Derby; Bridget, who in 1599 became wife of Francis, later
        second Lord Norris of Rycote; and Susan, who in 1604 became wife of
        Philip Herbert, first Earl of Montgomery.</note> the rest in other
        legacies. And his lands seme not so great as was thought, for
        <persName ref="#cecil-robert">Master Secretarie</persName><note>Sir
        Robert Cecil, son of Lord Burghley.</note> sayes his owne part will not
        rise to 1600 a yeare upon the racke.</p>

        <p>Yt is much laboured to make him Lord Treasurer wherin yf he fayle yt
        is assuredly thought he shalbe master of the wardes, for of necessitie
        there must be one by opinion of all the lawiers.
        <persName ref="#maynard-henry">Master Maynard</persName><note>Henry
        Maynard (knighted, 1602).</note> in goode earnest he is thought to be
        neerest in election and the rather for that
        <persName ref="#cecil-robert">Master Secretarie</persName> is become the
        Quenes man altogether for him. <orgName ref="#states-general">The
        States</orgName> are gon away well contented with such high favor that
        we have tied fast, by offring to pay our men of warre, garrisons and
        all, and to rembourse 30000 yearlie to the Quene till the whole debt be
        run out. Yet for all this yt is thought we shall treat, mary so that
        <orgName ref="#states-general">the States</orgName> must be included with
        theyre owne conditions.
        <persName ref="#cromwell-edward">The Lord Cromwell</persName><note>Edward,
        third Lord Cromwell.</note> sues hard and makes large offers for the
        government of the Brill, but yt is thought yf the warre go forward, that
        the Quene with <orgName ref="#states-general">the States</orgName>
        consent will translate that garrison to
        <placeName ref="#armagh">Armew</placeName> therby to have her forces
        neerer together and to assure herself the better of
        <placeName ref="#middelburg">Middleburgh</placeName> and the Yle of
        <placeName ref="#walcheren">Walkeren</placeName>. Yt is sayde your Lord
        Governor of <placeName ref="#ostend">Ostend</placeName><note>Sir Edward
        Norris, Governor of Ostend.</note> shall continue his place but most of
        your companies shalbe called away for
        <placeName ref="#ireland">Ireland</placeName>.</p>

        <p>We say that the late
        <persName ref="#albert-archduke">Cardinall Duke of Burgundie</persName><note>The
        Archduke Albert of Austria, formerly a Cardinal, who had surrendered his
        ecclesiastical office to govern the Spanish Netherlands and marry the
        Infanta.</note> is sworne and receved by 14 of the provinces and that
        presently he made proclamation that he meant to renounce all his
        <persName ref="#philip-ii">father in lawes</persName><note>Philip II of
        Spain.</note> quarrells, and to entertaine amitie with all his
        neighbours, specially the auncient allies and confederates of the house
        of Burgundie, and that Englishmen, Scottes and others might safely
        trafficke in all his dominions, and that
        <orgName ref="#states-general">the States</orgName> of Holland might
        likewise trade, go and come, with all securitie, during eight moneths
        till other order may be taken for continuance: and that within two
        moneths all straungers men of warre are to avoyde: further that he is
        gon into <placeName ref="#spain">Spaine</placeName> to fetch his
        bride,<note>The Infanta
        <persName ref="#isabella-infanta">Isabella Clara Eugenia</persName>,
        daughter of Philip II.</note> having obtained leave of the provinces to
        be absent one yeare, when discharged from theyre oth and obedience:
        wherby we gather (as yt is likewise reported) that the King of
        <placeName ref="#spain">Spaine</placeName> is certainly dead.<note>King
        <persName ref="#philip-ii">Philip II</persName> died September 3.</note>
        But these things must be better knowne to you neerer the market.</p>

        <p><persName ref="#bagnall-henry">Sir Henry Bagnoll</persName> the
        Marshall went with 3500 foot complete, and 300 horse to relieve the fort
        of <placeName ref="#blackwater">Blackwater</placeName> distressed by
        <persName ref="#oneill-hugh">Tiron</persName>,<note>Hugh O'Neill, second
        Earl of Tyrone.</note> and being come within two mile of yt, in a pass
        or woode where the ennemie had strongly intrenched himself was so
        furiously set upon that himself was there slaine with 16 other captaines
        and above 700 souldiers. The rest retired to
        <placeName ref="#armagh">Armagh</placeName> (having lost to the ennemie
        seventeen ensignes) not knowing how to tarry there or remove thence in
        safety, the ennemie being betwene ten and eight thousand strong: but
        newes came yesterday that they had made theire appointment, and that
        <persName ref="#oneill-hugh">Tiron</persName> out of his merciles bountie
        had graunted them leave to bury theyre dead and to go away with all they
        had, so that the fort might be delivered him, to the governor wherof
        <persName ref="#williams-thomas">Captaine Williams</persName><note>Thomas
        Williams, captain of the Blackwater fort.</note> and his souldiers he
        wold geve no better conditions then to depart in theyre dubletts and hose
        only with rapier and dagger. This is the greatest losse and dishonor the
        Quene hath had in her time, and yet yt seemes we are not moved more with
        yt, which whether yt proceed of more courage then of wit I know not, but
        I feare yt is rather a careles and insensible dulnes.</p>

        <p><persName ref="#bagnall-samuel">Sir Samuell Bagnoll</persName><note>Sir
        Samuel Bagenal, brother of Sir Henry.</note> went post for
        <placeName ref="#ireland">Ireland</placeName> on Satterday last, but his
        course and plot must be quite altered to go to
        <placeName ref="#lough-foyle">Loughfoile</placeName> for yt is to no
        purpose to go to the Blackwater now that the Blackwater is lost.
        <persName ref="#bingham-richard">Sir Richard Bingham</persName> hath ten
        dayes respite to set his thinges in order, and then to go Marshall of
        <placeName ref="#ireland">Ireland</placeName> with 5000 men, but I doubt
        yt wilbe rather in speach then in performance.
        <persName ref="#brooke-henry">The Lord Cobham</persName><note>Henry
        Brooke, Lord Cobham, who succeeded his father as Warden of the Cinque
        Ports.</note> was installed Lord Warden of the Cinq Ports on Bartlemew
        day at <placeName ref="#canterbury">Caunterbury</placeName>, at which
        solemnitie were assembled almost 4000 horse, and he kept the feast very
        magnificently and spent 26 oxen with all other provision sutable. He,
        <persName ref="#howard-thomas">the Lord Thomas Howard</persName>,
        <persName ref="#raleigh-walter">Sir Wal: Raleigh</persName> and
        <persName ref="#stanhope-john">Sir John Stanhop</persName><note>Sir John
        Stanhope (created Lord Stanhope of Harrington, 1605), Treasurer of the
        Chamber.</note> are in speach to be sworne shortly of the counsayle. Our
        marchants have lost two or three ships going to
        <placeName ref="#muscovy">Moscovie</placeName> and one is missing that
        shold come from thence.
        <persName ref="#danvers-charles">Sir Charles</persName> and
        <persName ref="#danvers-henry">Sir Henry Danvers</persName><note>Outlawed
        for the death of Henry Long in 1594, they took refuge in
        <placeName ref="#france">Fraunce</placeName> and distinguished themselves
        in the French Army. They were pardoned in June, 1598. Sir Charles Danvers
        was executed for his part in the Essex rebellion, 1601. Sir Henry Danvers
        was created Lord Danvers of Dauntsey in 1603 and Earl of Danby in
        1626.</note> are come. I saw them both yesterday.
        <persName ref="#scudamore-james">Sir James Scudamors</persName> lady<note>Mary,
        daughter of Peter Houghton, alderman of London.</note> that was so rich
        a manage is lately dead in childbed.</p>

        <p><persName ref="#vernon-elizabeth">Mistris Vernon</persName><note>Elizabeth,
        daughter of John Vernon of Hodnet, Shropshire, and one of the Queen's
        maids of honour. She became the wife of Henry Wriothesley, third Earl of
        Southampton.</note> hath taken a venew from the court, and lies in
        <placeName ref="#essex-house">Essex House</placeName>; some say she is
        under the girdle and swells upon yt, yet she plaines not of fowle play
        but sayes the <persName ref="#wriothesley-henry">erle of
        Southampton</persName> will justifie yt: and yt is bruited underhand
        that he was latelie here fowre dayes in great secret of purpose to marry
        her and that she comand effected yt accordingly.</p>

        <p>I thancke you for the letter you wrote me hence though yt were longe
        ere yt came to my hands. I met your
        <persName ref="#williams-alexander">Alexander</persName> and
        Bucephalus<note>Probably Alexander Williams and his wife, Carleton's
        sister Elizabeth.</note> at
        <persName ref="#spencer-william">Sir William Spencers</persName>,<note>Probably
        at his house at Yarnton, Oxfordshire.</note> and delivered his letter to
        your brother <persName ref="#carleton-george">Carleton</persName> for he
        challenged yt as by your appointment though he shewed no commission. And
        thus having wearied both my self and you I bid you farewell and commit
        you to God.</p>

        <closer>
          <dateline>From <placeName ref="#london">London</placeName> this
          <date when="1598-08-30">30th of August 1598</date>.</dateline>
          <signed>Yours most assuredly<lb/>
          <persName ref="#chamberlain-john">JOHN CHAMBERLAIN</persName>.</signed>
        </closer>

        <postscript>
          <p><address><addrLine>To my very goode frend Master
          <persName ref="#carleton-dudley">Dudley Carleton</persName> attending
          on the Lord Governor of
          <placeName ref="#ostend">Ostend</placeName> geve these.</addrLine></address></p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div type="editor-note">
        <head>Editor's Note</head>
        <p>Written from London on 30 August 1598, this is the richest letter of the early sequence. Chamberlain arrived back in London from Oxfordshire — having traveled with Rowland Lytton — just in time for the funeral of William Cecil, Lord Burghley, who had died on August 4. He reports on the ceremony, the conspicuous grief (or political calculation) of the Earl of Essex, and the state of Burghley's estate and the Queen's treasury. The letter then turns to the succession question: whether Robert Cecil will become Lord Treasurer or Master of the Wards, and the role of Henry Maynard in the factional maneuvering. The Dutch States-General depart apparently satisfied, though an Anglo-Spanish peace is still under discussion. The Archduke Albert has been received by the Spanish Netherlands provinces and proclaimed peace with England and Scotland; there are rumours that Philip II is dead (he died September 3). The letter's darkest passage concerns the Battle of the Yellow Ford (August 14), where Sir Henry Bagenal, the Marshal of Ireland, was killed alongside sixteen captains and over seven hundred soldiers — the worst English military defeat in Ireland in living memory. The Blackwater fort is surrendered on humiliating terms, its garrison stripped to doublet and hose. Chamberlain then moves to the domestic and social register: Lord Cobham's installation as Lord Warden of the Cinque Ports, the return of the pardoned Danvers brothers, the death of Lady Scudamore in childbed, and the explosive news of Elizabeth Vernon's secret pregnancy and marriage to the Earl of Southampton. The letter closes with a casual note about meeting Carleton's brother-in-law Alexander Williams at Sir William Spencer's.</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
