<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Letter from John Chamberlain to Dudley Carleton, 31 May 1598</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editor</resp>
          <name>Brandon Taylor</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Published digitally at earlymodernletters.org. Licensed under CC BY 4.0.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>The Letters of John Chamberlain</title>
          <editor>Norman Egbert McClure</editor>
          <pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>
          <publisher>American Philosophical Society</publisher>
          <date when="1939">1939</date>
          <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
          <biblScope unit="page">39–41</biblScope>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="letter-meta">
        <head>Letter Metadata</head>
        <p><date when="1598-05-31">31 May 1598</date></p>
        <p><placeName ref="#london">London</placeName></p>
        <p><correspDesc>
          <correspAction type="sent">
            <persName ref="#chamberlain-john">John Chamberlain</persName>
            <date when="1598-05-31"/>
            <placeName ref="#london">London</placeName>
          </correspAction>
          <correspAction type="received">
            <persName ref="#carleton-dudley">Dudley Carleton</persName>
            <placeName ref="#ostend">Ostend</placeName>
          </correspAction>
        </correspDesc></p>
      </div>
    </front>

    <body>
      <div type="letter-text">

        <p>Though I have not heard from you since I wrote last, neither have
        we any novelties greatly worth the writing, yet being to go out of
        towne to morrow towards <placeName ref="#ascott">Askot</placeName>,
        me thinckes I must needs bid you farewell.</p>

        <p>Your frend <persName ref="#edmondes-thomas">Edmonds</persName><note>Thomas
        Edmondes (knighted, 1603).</note> came out of
        <placeName ref="#france">Fraunce</placeName> the last weeke and bringes
        worde that the peace there is so forward that yt lackes nothing but the
        publishinge,<note>The peace was publicly proclaimed May 26.</note> which
        is thought to be performed by this time, and all the townes upon the
        point of deliverie. He is like to be tossed to and fro and
        brickewald<note>Corruption of French <hi rend="italics">bricoler</hi>,
        associated by popular etymology with the brick wall of the tennis
        court.</note> like a tennis ball from the one side to the other somwhat
        to be concluded: for we have two moneths time to deliberate whether we
        will treat or no, and three moneths more for the treaty: wherupon we are
        not yet fully resolved but consult dayly about yt and the further they
        looke into yt the more difficulties appeare, insomuch that the wisest
        judgements are distracted and know not what to choose; for mine owne
        part having heard what hath bin sayde <hi rend="italics" xml:lang="la">pro
        et contra</hi> on both sides, I cannot well discerne whether were better
        an insidious peace, or so faint and weake a warre as we have made
        hitherto and are like to do hereafter, which doth rather prolonge and
        drawe on the consumption then remedie the disease. In the meane time the
        state of <placeName ref="#ireland">Ireland</placeName> stands in yll
        termes, for we are so wholly possest with this ymaginarie peace that we
        cannot attend yt. Not past eight dayes since it was decreed that
        <persName ref="#bingham-richard">Sir Rich: Bingham</persName>,
        <persName ref="#bagnall-samuel">Sir Samuell Bagnoll</persName> and
        <persName ref="#docwra-henry">Sir Henry Docwray</persName> shold be sent
        thether with ech of them a regiment of 2000: but that course is altered
        and now they talke that <persName ref="#raleigh-walter">Sir W.
        Raleigh</persName> and <persName ref="#carew-george">Sir George
        Carew</persName><note>Of Clopton, Warwickshire. He was created Lord
        Carew of Clopton in 1605, and Earl of Totnes in 1626.</note> shold
        undertake yt, but how longe that will hold is uncertain.</p>

        <p><persName ref="#zouche-edward">Zouch</persName><note>Edward, eleventh
        Lord Zouche of Harringworth, and
        <persName ref="#perkins-christopher">Christopher Perkins</persName>
        (knighted, 1603).</note> with
        <persName ref="#perkins-christopher">Dr. Parkins</persName> is going
        ambassador into <placeName ref="#denmark">Denmarke</placeName> with
        certain secret instructions to go into
        <placeName ref="#poland">Poland</placeName> likewise about a Dutch baron.
        The newes I wrote of <persName ref="#blount-charles">Sir Charles
        Blunt</persName> must be recalled for yt was a mistaking of a combat
        that passed betwene a Frenchman and a Dutchman that was knighted at
        Cales. Bluet in Britain is sayde to be rased. One
        <persName ref="#cary-george">Cary</persName><note>George Carew
        (knighted, 1603), son of Thomas Carew of Antony, and secretary to
        <persName ref="#egerton-thomas">Sir Thomas Egerton</persName>.</note>
        is appointed secretarie to the Lord Keper for such busines.
        <persName ref="#vere-francis">Sir Fra: Vere</persName> is to go very
        shortly to <orgName ref="#states-general">the States</orgName>. The
        Lord bishop of <placeName ref="#gloucester">Glocester</placeName><note>John
        Bullingham.</note> is lately dead. All your private frends are as you
        left them, and so wishing the continuance of your health and welfare I
        commit you to God.</p>

        <closer>
          <dateline>From <placeName ref="#london">London</placeName> this
          <date when="1598-05-31">last of May 1598</date>.</dateline>
          <signed>Your assured frend<lb/>
          <persName ref="#chamberlain-john">JOHN CHAMBERLAIN</persName>.</signed>
        </closer>

        <postscript>
          <p><address><addrLine>To my very goode frend Master
          <persName ref="#carleton-dudley">Dudley Carleton</persName> attending
          on the Lord Governor of
          <placeName ref="#ostend">Ostend</placeName> geve these.</addrLine></address></p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div type="editor-note">
        <head>Editor's Note</head>
        <p>Written from London on 31 May 1598, the day before Chamberlain was to leave for Ascott, this letter offers his most sustained meditation on the question of Anglo-Spanish peace. Thomas Edmondes has returned from France reporting the peace all but concluded (it was proclaimed on May 26), but Chamberlain is genuinely uncertain whether peace is better than the half-hearted war England has waged. The letter's central passage weighs the risks: Dutch commercial exclusion, the worsening situation in Ireland, and the general paralysis of English policy. He reports that the original plan to send Bingham, Bagnall, and Docwra to Ireland with regiments has been scrapped in favour of an alternative involving Raleigh and Sir George Carew, which he expects will also come to nothing. A final miscellany covers the Zouche-Perkins embassy to Denmark and Poland, the correction of Chamberlain's earlier report about Sir Charles Blount's duel (which was actually a different fight altogether), the reported demolition of the Spanish fort at Blavet in Brittany, a new appointment as secretary to the Lord Keeper, Sir Francis Vere's imminent departure for the States, and the death of the Bishop of Gloucester.</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
