<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Letter from John Chamberlain to Dudley Carleton, 8 November 1598</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editor</resp>
          <name>Brandon Taylor</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Published digitally at earlymodernletters.org. Licensed under CC BY 4.0.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>The Letters of John Chamberlain</title>
          <editor>Norman Egbert McClure</editor>
          <pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>
          <publisher>American Philosophical Society</publisher>
          <date when="1939">1939</date>
          <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
          <biblScope unit="page">50–53</biblScope>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="letter-meta">
        <head>Letter Metadata</head>
        <p><date when="1598-11-08">8 November 1598</date></p>
        <p><placeName ref="#london">London</placeName></p>
        <p><correspDesc>
          <correspAction type="sent">
            <persName ref="#chamberlain-john">John Chamberlain</persName>
            <date when="1598-11-08"/>
            <placeName ref="#london">London</placeName>
          </correspAction>
          <correspAction type="received">
            <persName ref="#carleton-dudley">Dudley Carleton</persName>
            <placeName ref="#ostend">Ostend</placeName>
          </correspAction>
        </correspDesc></p>
      </div>
    </front>

    <body>
      <div type="letter-text">
        <opener>Master Carleton,</opener>

        <p>Your letters of the 23th of the last came sixe or eight dayes since, and I have staide
          the longer to aunswer them in hope somwhat wold fall out worth the writing, and withall
          I had another lay on my handes for want of cariage, for though with much search I found
          out where the post of Sandwich lay yet not having any body there to direct yt unto, or
          that wold take care to send yt over I wold not commit yt altogether to hap hasard; upon
          inquiry I learne there is one Master Robinson might do yt very conveniently yf either of
          us had any acquaintaunce with him. Our court causes are still <hi rend="italic">in statu
          quo prius</hi>, and no more certainty what will become of any of those places then when
          I wrote you last. Only they have resolved upon
          <persName ref="#neville-henry">Master Nevill</persName><note>Henry Neville
          (c. 1564–1615), diplomat and MP for Berkshire. Despite his earnest suit to the contrary,
          he was confirmed as ambassador to France and given orders to make himself ready before
          Christmas. He was knighted after his appointment; see Letter 9 for his earlier
          nomination.</note> for Fraunce and (for all his earnest sute to the contrary) he hath
          warning to make himself redy this and Christmas. The Frenchman that is come is
          <hi rend="italic">de robbe longue</hi><note><persName ref="#thumery-de-boissise">Le
          Sieur Thumery de Boissise</persName>, who arrived at Dover on 14 October 1598 and remained
          as ambassador until 1601. <hi rend="italic">De robbe longue</hi> means of the long robe —
          a civilian lawyer rather than a military man; see Letter 9. He was brother-in-law to
          the president of the Parlement of Harlay.</note>, brother in law to him that was here
          this time twelvemoneth having maried two sisters daughters to the president of Harle. We
          heare the French king is sicke of a caruncle or carnosite in his yard which is thought
          wilbe a very difficult cure.<note>A caruncle is a fleshy morbid growth; "his yard" is
          the penis. Henri IV was suffering from a urogenital complaint in autumn 1598, a detail
          Chamberlain relays with characteristic anatomical candour.</note> When I wrote you last
          we did but suspect the kindling of a fire in
          <placeName ref="#ireland">Ireland</placeName> which is since broken out into an open
          flame, so far foorth that unles there be present help yt is feared all wilbe gon; for we
          heare of new conspiracies every day, and there was a plot layde to betray
          <placeName ref="#dublin">Dublin</placeName>; and besides that the people are generally
          (as well in respect of religion as for other alliances) inclined to the rebells, the
          townes begin to stagger and refuse to receve garrison. Those of
          <placeName ref="#munster">Mounster</placeName> have set up a new
          <persName ref="#fitzgerald-james">Desmond</persName><note>James Fitzthomas Fitzgerald,
          who assumed the title of Earl of Desmond with backing from the Pope and the Irish
          confederacy; see Letter 9. He was known as the Súgán Earl, from the Irish
          <hi rend="italic">súgán</hi> (a straw rope), implying the illegitimacy of his
          claim.</note> (by the Popes meanes as is saide), and persecute our English undertakers
          that were planted in those partes with all manner of villanie and barbarous crueltie.
          The erle of
          <persName ref="#butler-thomas-ormond">Ormond</persName><note>Thomas Butler
          (1531–1614), tenth Earl of Ormond, known as "Black Tom Butler." The most powerful
          Anglo-Irish magnate loyal to the crown, and a long-standing favourite of Elizabeth I.
          His county of Tipperary was directly exposed to rebel incursions by autumn 1598, giving
          him personal as well as political motives to act.</note> hath sent over in post for 2000
          men which are making redy with all possible haste, and yt is looked he shold do other
          manner of service then he hath don hitherto now that yt toucheth his freehold and that
          the fire is come so neere him that yt hath almost consumed his countie of Tipperare. Yt
          is generally held that the erle of
          <persName ref="#devereux-robert">Essex</persName> shall go thether towards the spring
          as lieutenant generall, and the
          <persName ref="#blount-charles">Lord Mountjoy</persName> as his Lord Deputie with
          divers other younge lordes and noble men: and that he shalbe accompanied with the most
          part of those knights that be his creatures, for yt is thought fit they shold not come
          too easilie by theyre honor, but that in this case as well as in many others yt should
          be graunted for service don and to be don. We looke to morrow for the arraignment of
          <persName ref="#stanley-john">Stanly</persName>,
          <persName ref="#rolles">Rolles</persName>,
          <persName ref="#squire-edward">Squire</persName><note>Edward Squire (d. 1598),
          a ship's steward who had been captured by the Spanish and converted into an agent. He
          confessed to attempting to poison the pommel of Essex's saddle and to infecting the
          Queen's chair-arm with a poisonous ointment. He was hanged and quartered on
          23 November 1598. (<hi rend="italic">Cal. S. P. Dom.</hi>, 1598–1601,
          pp. 107–110, 111–112; Camden, <hi rend="italic">Annales</hi>,
          pp. 498–499.)</note> and the rest of that crue.</p>

        <p>The report goes of very fowle matters discovered, and some part attempted by them; as
          theyre trialls fall out you shall heare more by my next. The Imperiall
          <persName ref="#arundell-thomas">Count Arundell</persName><note>Thomas Arundell
          (c. 1560–1639), son of Sir Matthew Arundell of Wardour Castle. Created Count of the
          Holy Roman Empire by the Emperor Rudolf II in 1595 for his service against the Turks
          in Hungary — a title that proved controversial in England. He was now committed for
          having held conversations with Stanley; he was later created Lord Arundell of Wardour
          in 1605.</note> is committed, who had some conferences with
          <persName ref="#stanley-john">Stanly</persName>; [he is committed] to the keping of
          <persName ref="#herbert-john">Dr. Harbert</persName> at his first arrivall. The new
          Countesse of
          <persName ref="#wriothesley-henry">Southampton</persName>,
          <persName ref="#vernon-elizabeth">my Lady</persName>,<note>Elizabeth Vernon
          (c. 1572–1655), maid of honour to Queen Elizabeth, who had secretly married Henry
          Wriothesley, third Earl of Southampton, earlier in 1598 while pregnant. Their
          clandestine marriage had incensed the Queen; see Letter 6. The child, a daughter, was
          Penelope Wriothesley.</note> is brought a bed of a daughter, and to mend her portion
          the erle her father hath lately lost 18000 crownes at tennis in
          <placeName ref="#paris">Paris</placeName>.<note>The phrase "the erle her father" most
          likely refers to Southampton himself, as father of the newborn daughter. Southampton
          was in France at this time, and the 18,000 crowns lost at tennis would be characteristic
          of the financial recklessness that kept his affairs unsettled throughout this
          period.</note></p>

        <p><persName ref="#southwell-robert">Sir Robert Southwell</persName><note>Sir Robert
          Southwell (1561–1598), soldier and diplomat; served in Ireland and the Low Countries.
          He died in late October 1598. His widow, Elizabeth, was daughter of Charles Howard,
          first Earl of Nottingham.</note> is dead and hath left his lady a rich widow. The Quene
          hath geven the
          <persName ref="#fitzgerald-frances-kildare">Countesse of Kildare</persName><note>Frances
          Howard (d. 1628), daughter of Charles Howard, first Earl of Nottingham, and widow of
          Henry Fitzgerald, twelfth Earl of Kildare (d. 1597). Her jointure from the Kildare
          estates had been disrupted by the Irish rebellion, prompting the Queen's award of an
          annuity.</note> 700<hi rend="italic">li</hi> a yeare out of the exchecquer in
          recompence of her jointure spoyled in
          <placeName ref="#ireland">Irland</placeName>. The
          <persName ref="#savile-henry">warden of Marton Colledge</persName><note>Henry Savile
          (1549–1622), scholar, editor of Chrysostom and Tacitus; Warden of Merton College,
          Oxford, from 1585, and Provost of Eton from 1596. He was engaged throughout the 1590s
          in a contentious disciplinary struggle with certain Merton fellows; knighted in
          1604.</note> hath got a great victorie of his fellowes and raunsommed the rest expelled
          and punished amongst them, of whom
          <persName ref="#colmer-jasper">Master Colmer</persName><note>Jasper Colmer, proctor
          of Merton College; expelled in the course of the warden's disciplinary proceedings.
          According to Chamberlain, he died within five days, of grief or — as Chamberlain puts
          it — "curst hart."</note> died within five dayes after of greife or curst hart.
          <persName ref="#reynolds-john">Dr. Raynolds</persName><note>John Reynolds (also
          Rainolds; 1549–1607), Puritan divine, theologian, and biblical scholar. Elected
          President of Corpus Christi College, Oxford, in 1598; later a principal instigator of
          the King James Bible (1611). Chamberlain notes that he exchanged his position at
          Lincoln College with Dr. William Cole.</note> is head of Corpus Christi Colledge having
          exchaunged Lincoln with
          <persName ref="#cole-william">Dr. Cole</persName>.<note>William Cole (d. 1600),
          clergyman; took up a position at Lincoln College, Oxford, when Reynolds moved to
          Corpus Christi.</note> The king of
          <placeName ref="#spain">Spaine</placeName> is saide to have staid all the Hollanders,
          and all Irish ships that have not the earle of
          <persName ref="#oneill-hugh">Tirons</persName> passe. I had almost forgot to recall
          the killing of
          <persName ref="#bagnall-samuel">Sir Samuell Bagnoll</persName>, for yt falles out to
          be nothing so, and yet was yt current both in court and countrie above ten dayes
          together.
          <persName ref="#ortelius-abraham">Ortelius</persName> his <hi rend="italic">Thesaurus
          Geographicus</hi><note>Abraham Ortelius (1527–1598), Flemish cartographer and creator
          of the <hi rend="italic">Theatrum Orbis Terrarum</hi> (1570). He had died in June 1598;
          Chamberlain refers to his <hi rend="italic">Thesaurus Geographicus</hi> (expanded
          edition, 1596), a geographical dictionary that
          <persName ref="#lytton-rowland">Rowland Lytton</persName> is sending to
          Carleton. The book's bulk made it impossible to send by ordinary post.</note> is too
          bigg to be sent by an ordinarie messenger, and therfore yt must stay till your boat come
          or that you send other order; your cousen
          <persName ref="#lytton-rowland">Lytton</persName> will needs bestow yt on you, wherin
          I made no longe strife. I sent your letter to the
          <persName ref="#north-anne">Lady Northes</persName><note>Anne North (née Rich;
          d. 1616), wife of Roger North, second Baron North, of Kirtling Hall,
          Cambridgeshire. Carleton evidently had ties to the North household, though Chamberlain
          found them socially exacting: he complains that they return his letters rather than
          forwarding them, and give him no direction for sending his own.</note> because she lies
          far of, and the wether hath ben so exceding fowle that I stir litle abrode, neither am
          I overhastie to come there, they be so apt to take toyes and become so numerous that
          they send backe your letters when I desire they wold convay them, or geve me any
          direction how I might send myself. But I will find a time to visit them, because you
          wish yt, and for the auncient goodwill and kindly affection that hath past betwene us,
          in which respect I will alwayes be redy to do them the best service I can. And so
          wishing you all health and welfare I commit you to God.</p>

        <closer>
          <dateline>From <placeName ref="#london">London</placeName> this
            <date when="1598-11-08">8th of November 1598</date>.</dateline>
          <signed>Yours most assuredly,
            <persName ref="#chamberlain-john">JOHN CHAMBERLAIN</persName>.</signed>
        </closer>

        <postscript>
          <p>To my very goode frend Master
            <persName ref="#carleton-dudley">Dudley Carleton</persName> attending on the Lord
            Governor of <placeName ref="#ostend">Ostend</placeName> geve these.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
