<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Letter from John Chamberlain to Dudley Carleton, 31 January 1599</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editor</resp>
          <name>Brandon Taylor</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Published digitally at earlymodernletters.org. Licensed under CC BY 4.0.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>The Letters of John Chamberlain</title>
          <editor>Norman Egbert McClure</editor>
          <pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>
          <publisher>American Philosophical Society</publisher>
          <date when="1939">1939</date>
          <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
          <biblScope unit="page">65–67</biblScope>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="letter-meta">
        <head>Letter Metadata</head>
        <p><date when="1599-01-31">31 January 1599</date></p>
        <p><placeName ref="#london">London</placeName></p>
        <p><correspDesc>
          <correspAction type="sent">
            <persName ref="#chamberlain-john">John Chamberlain</persName>
            <date when="1599-01-31"/>
            <placeName ref="#london">London</placeName>
          </correspAction>
          <correspAction type="received">
            <persName ref="#carleton-dudley">Dudley Carleton</persName>
            <placeName ref="#ostend">Ostend</placeName>
          </correspAction>
        </correspDesc></p>
      </div>
    </front>

    <body>
      <div type="letter-text">
        <opener>Goode Master Carleton,</opener>

        <p>I receved your letters of the first and ninth of this present very lately, and marvayle
          you had not heard of your skipper before that time. I pray God all be well with him, and
          that he have not miscaried, for you had rich adventure in him of the <hi rend="italic">Thesaurus
          Geographicus</hi>,<note>The <hi rend="italic">Thesaurus Geographicus</hi> of
          <persName ref="#ortelius-abraham">Abraham Ortelius</persName> had been promised to
          Carleton since Letter 10 and dispatched by special bearer in Letter 12, at
          <persName ref="#lytton-rowland">Rowland Lytton</persName>'s expense. It was apparently
          sent by a skipper — a ship's captain sailing to Ostend — who has now gone silent.
          Chamberlain's worry is practical: Carleton had a valuable cargo at risk.</note> sent by
          your cousen
          <persName ref="#lytton-rowland">Lytton</persName>, who is now in towne, and commends
          him to you. Your brother
          <persName ref="#carleton-george">Carleton</persName> is at length come, and the
          Thesaurus not yet come to you; and for your other private frends here is no chaunge.</p>

        <p>The erle of
          <persName ref="#devereux-robert">Essex</persName> his commission for
          <placeName ref="#ireland">Ireland</placeName> is after many difficulties agreed on,
          though not yet signed. He hath the name of Lieutenant,<note>Lord Lieutenant General of
          Ireland — the highest military-viceregal designation in the crown's gift, outranking
          the more usual title of Lord Deputy. Essex had insisted on this superior designation
          from the outset. His commission was reportedly the most sweeping ever issued for Ireland:
          beyond the lieutenant-general's title it granted him power to create barons, to return
          at his own discretion, and to dispose of lands won from the rebels — prerogatives
          that gave a faction of the council serious pause.</note> [power to create] a baron or
          two, may returne at pleasure, make and dispose of such landes as shalbe won from the
          rebells at his goode liking, and many other such points are spoken of, but how truly
          <hi rend="italic">viderit successus</hi>:<note>"Let the outcome be seen" — the outcome
          will tell. Chamberlain's dry Latinate reserve: the paper powers are impressive; whether
          they will survive contact with Irish reality is another question.</note> he makes great
          provision for horses, and many are presented him. They talke likewise of carrienge over
          two or three hundreth mastives<note>Mastiffs — large war-dogs bred for combat. The plan
          to deploy them against Irish cattle was a scorched-earth tactic: starving rebel
          communities by killing their livestock. As Chamberlain mildly observes, the target would
          be the cattle rather than the people themselves. The scheme was discussed but never
          carried out.</note> to werry the
          <placeName ref="#ireland">Irish</placeName> or rather (as I take yt) theyre cattell.</p>

        <p>The preasse of his followers wilbe much abated by reason the Quene countermaundes many,
          as namely first all her owne servants, and the erle of
          <persName ref="#manners-roger">Rutland</persName> and the Lord
          <persName ref="#grey-thomas-wilton">Gray</persName>,
          <persName ref="#parker-nicholas">Sir Nicolas Parker</persName>,
          <persName ref="#gorges-ferdinando">Sir Ferdinando Gorge</persName>,
          <persName ref="#yorke-edward">Sir Edward Yorke</persName>,
          <persName ref="#berkeley-john">Sir John Barkclay</persName>,
          <persName ref="#brooke-john">Sir John Brooke</persName>,
          <persName ref="#blount-charles">Sir Charles Blunt</persName>,
          <persName ref="#egerton-thomas-jr">Sir Thomas Egerton</persName>,<note>Not Thomas
          Egerton the Lord Keeper (already in his late fifties and a principal officer of state),
          but a younger soldier of the same name — possibly a son or near kinsman — who appears
          as one of Essex's intended colonels here countermanded from the Irish
          expedition.</note>
          <persName ref="#jermyn-thomas">Sir Thomas Germin</persName>,
          <persName ref="#danvers-charles">Sir Charles Davers</persName>, and divers other that
          come not now in my way. Some suspect yt is his owne doing because he is not able to
          geve them all satisfaction, but I am not of that opinion.<note>The Queen's mass
          countermand of Essex's followers was widely read as a deliberate check on his military
          patronage. Chamberlain, with characteristic moderation, refuses to attribute the
          dismissals to Essex himself — who, he implies, would have strained to accommodate so
          many ambitious clients had the Queen allowed it.</note></p>

        <p>He hath dealt well aforehand with Cap:
          <persName ref="#davies-john-captain">John Davis</persName><note>Captain John Davies
          (sometimes Davis), soldier and military administrator. The surveyorship of the
          ordnance — the crown officer responsible for equipping artillery and munitions — was a
          permanent administrative post, not dependent on the Irish expedition's outcome. "A
          place will stick by him howsoever this journey succeed" is Chamberlain's way of noting
          that Essex has done Davies a lasting good turn regardless of what happens in
          Ireland.</note> and put him in possession of survayor of the ordinaunce, which is a
          place will sticke by him howsoever this jorny succeed. The unkindenes twixt him and
          others is not yet reconciled,<note>The quarrel between
          <persName ref="#devereux-robert">Essex</persName> and
          <persName ref="#howard-charles">the Lord Admiral</persName> (Charles Howard, Earl of
          Nottingham) over Sir William Woodhouse's regiment, described in Letter 15, remains
          unresolved. Chamberlain feared it would poison the Irish venture from the start.</note>
          which no doubt will much hinder this action that had need of all furtheraunce.</p>

        <p>Newes came lately thence that
          <persName ref="#bingham-richard">Sir Richard Bingham</persName> is dead,<note>Richard
          Bingham (1528–1599), soldier and President of Connacht, had suppressed Connacht with
          considerable brutality for over a decade. Sent back to Ireland in late 1598 to shore
          up the collapsing military situation, he fell ill almost immediately after reaching
          Dublin. His death removes the most experienced English administrator in Connacht at
          the worst possible moment.</note> and that the erle of
          <persName ref="#butler-thomas-ormond">Ormond</persName> hath geven the rebells a blow
          in relieving a fort and slaine 3 or 400 in which incounter
          <persName ref="#power-henry">Sir Henry Poore</persName><note>Sir Henry Power (c.
          1562–1621), knighted in 1599; later created first Viscount Valentia (1621). He was
          an English officer serving in Ireland. A musket-ball lodged in the skull was an
          extremely dangerous wound; that the ball "remains there" but Power was expected to
          survive suggests either a fortunate trajectory or wishful
          thinking.</note> receved a shot in the head which remaines there, but yt is thought
          without daunger.</p>

        <p>Here is a great and curious present going to the great
          <persName ref="#mehmed-iii">Turke</persName><note>Mehmed III (1566–1603), Ottoman
          Sultan. The "curious present" was an elaborate self-playing mechanical organ built by
          Thomas Dallam, the London organ-maker, commissioned by Queen Elizabeth. Dallam sailed
          to Constantinople in 1599 to install it and left a lively diary of the voyage. The
          diplomatic scandal Chamberlain anticipates — and specifically among Protestant German
          states — arose because England's cultivation of the Ottoman Sultan as an ally against
          Catholic Spain looked to many Protestant neighbours like trafficking with
          infidels.</note> which no doubt wilbe much talked of, and be very scandalous among
          other nations specially the Germans. Upon the Duke of
          <persName ref="#medici-ferdinand">Florence</persName> his embargo and complaint of our
          piracies, here is order taken upon paine of death that no prises be taken in the
          <placeName ref="#levant">Levant</placeName> seas.<note>Ferdinand I de' Medici
          (1549–1609), Grand Duke of Tuscany, had been pressing London about English privateers
          seizing Florentine and Tuscan vessels in the eastern Mediterranean. The severity of
          the penalty — death — reflects both the seriousness of the diplomatic complaint and
          the commercial stakes: the Levant Company's trade to Constantinople, Aleppo, and
          Alexandria was among the most profitable in the English economy.</note></p>

        <p>We are like enough to fall at some odds with the
          <persName ref="#henry-iv-france">French king</persName><note>Henri IV of France
          (1553–1610), who had converted from Protestantism to Catholicism in 1593 to claim the
          throne ("Paris is worth a mass"). The trade policy Chamberlain describes was a
          straightforwardly mercantilist response to France's dependency on imported finished
          textiles: by banning them, Henri intended to stimulate domestic manufacturing and
          ship-building in order to capture Iberian trade for French merchants. For England,
          whose cloth exports underpinned the entire commercial economy, the prospect was
          alarming.</note> about his trafficke into
          <placeName ref="#spain">Spaine</placeName>, for of late (meaning to set his people on
          worke and make them industrious) he hath forbidden all manner of wrought silkes to be
          brought into his dominions, or any worke made of wollen, (which is contrary to our
          former contracts of entercourse) and withall doth incourage his people all he can to
          build and buy shippes thereby to get the whole trade of
          <placeName ref="#spain">Spaine</placeName>, wherin yf he be not prevented, he will sone
          begger both the Hollanders and us, and hereafter we shall have more ado with him and
          his then ever we had with the Spaniard. Here hath ben much contesting about yt with his
          ambassador, and that hotly inough, but we have the wolfe by the eares and know not
          how to hold him nor how to let him go.</p>

        <p>The Quenes want of mony is not yet so fully supplied but that they are faine to descend
          to mean men, and picke yt up here and there as they can get yt, and you must thincke
          they were neere driven when they found out me as a fit man to lend mony, but I thincke
          I aunswered them sufficiently, that where nothing is to be had the Quene must loose her
          right.<note>One of the few moments in the correspondence where Chamberlain makes himself
          the subject. Pressed by crown collectors for a forced loan, he pleaded poverty —
          invoking the legal maxim that where no assets exist, the sovereign forfeits the claim —
          and apparently got away with it. The self-deprecating tone barely conceals considerable
          satisfaction.</note> There is a sale in hand of 3000<hi rend="italic">li</hi> of the
          Quenes land, which is thought will help well to stop a gap.</p>

        <p>Yt is geven out that the Lord
          <persName ref="#compton-william">Compton</persName><note>William Compton, later first
          Earl of Northampton (1568–1630). His marriage to Elizabeth Spencer became one of the
          celebrated romantic stories of the late Elizabethan period: Sir John Spencer, reportedly
          furious at the match, was said to have been outmanoeuvred when Lord Compton spirited his
          daughter out of the house concealed in a basket. Whether or not the basket story is
          true, Chamberlain's framing — "it is given out" — suggests the engagement was not yet
          public knowledge in late January 1599.</note> shall marry our Sir
          <persName ref="#spencer-john-london">John Spensers</persName><note>Sir John Spencer
          (c. 1548–1610), Lord Mayor of London 1594–95 and one of the wealthiest men in England,
          known as "Rich Spencer." His fortune came from the Levant trade and cloth dealing.
          The marriage terms Chamberlain gives — £10,000 down plus redemption of £18,000 in
          mortgaged land — were a substantial settlement that would have cleared most of
          Compton's encumbrances.</note> daughter of
          <placeName ref="#london">London</placeName>, on these conditions that he geve him
          10000<hi rend="italic">li</hi> redy mony with her, and redeeme his land that lieth in
          morgage for 18000<hi rend="italic">li</hi> more.</p>

        <p>Sir
          <persName ref="#harvey-william">William Harvies</persName> marriage with the old
          countesse of
          <persName ref="#wriothesley-mary">Southampton</persName><note>Mary Browne (d. 1607),
          widow of Henry Wriothesley, second Earl of Southampton, and subsequently of Sir Thomas
          Heneage. She was the mother of Henry Wriothesley, third Earl — Essex's current
          protégé. The marriage to Sir William Harvey had been rumoured since Letter 4 (May 1598)
          and had evidently been contracted in secret; only now, eight months later, does
          Chamberlain report it "coming to be published."</note> that hath lien smothering so
          longe, comes now to be published. I send you here certaine odde epitaphes and epigrammes
          that go under the name of pasquills. And thus with my harty commendations I commit you
          to God. Touching
          <placeName ref="#flushing">Vlushing</placeName><note>Vlissingen (Flushing), the
          cautionary town in Zeeland held by England as security for its Dutch loans. Carleton
          was serving in the garrison under the Lord Governor, Sir Francis Vere. Any shift in
          England's grip on the cautionary towns was diplomatically sensitive; Chamberlain's
          brief "no alteration" was reassurance that the question had not moved in either
          direction.</note> I heare of no alteration.</p>

        <closer>
          <dateline>From <placeName ref="#london">London</placeName> this
            <date when="1599-01-31">last of January 1599</date>.</dateline>
          <signed>Yours most assuredly,
            <persName ref="#chamberlain-john">JOHN CHAMBERLAIN</persName>.</signed>
        </closer>

        <postscript>
          <p>To my very goode frend Master
            <persName ref="#carleton-dudley">Dudley Carleton</persName> attending on the Lord
            Governor of <placeName ref="#ostend">Ostend</placeName> geve these.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
