<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Letter from John Chamberlain to Dudley Carleton, 17 September 1598</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editor</resp>
          <name>Brandon Taylor</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Published digitally at earlymodernletters.org. Licensed under CC BY 4.0.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>The Letters of John Chamberlain</title>
          <editor>Norman Egbert McClure</editor>
          <pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>
          <publisher>American Philosophical Society</publisher>
          <date when="1939">1939</date>
          <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
          <biblScope unit="page">45–46</biblScope>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="letter-meta">
        <head>Letter Metadata</head>
        <p><date when="1598-09-17">17 September 1598</date></p>
        <p><placeName ref="#knebworth">Knebworth</placeName></p>
        <p><correspDesc>
          <correspAction type="sent">
            <persName ref="#chamberlain-john">John Chamberlain</persName>
            <date when="1598-09-17"/>
            <placeName ref="#knebworth">Knebworth</placeName>
          </correspAction>
          <correspAction type="received">
            <persName ref="#carleton-dudley">Dudley Carleton</persName>
            <placeName ref="#ostend">Ostend</placeName>
          </correspAction>
        </correspDesc></p>
      </div>
    </front>

    <body>
      <div type="letter-text">
        <p>I heard not of this messengers being here, nor of his intended jorny to
          <placeName ref="#ostend">Ostend</placeName> till he was almost going; and though I had
          known yt sooner, yet could I not have writ you much more then I am like to do on this
          sodain: for here growes no newes at
          <placeName ref="#knebworth">Knebworth</placeName>,<note>The Hertfordshire house of
          <persName ref="#lytton-rowland">Rowland Lytton</persName>.</note> unles I shold tell you
          how well harvest is come home, or some other adventures of hawking, hunting, bowlinge or
          such like. But what I want of mine owne store I will borrow of my neighbours, and for
          brevities sake in this haste send you a letter I receved fowre or five dayes since that
          shewes how the world went at the writing thereof, whereto I can only adde that this day
          sevenight the erle of
          <persName ref="#devereux-robert">Essex</persName> went to the court but with what
          successe, or how matters stand since, I know not.<note><persName ref="#devereux-robert">Essex</persName>
          took his place in the Council on September 10. (<hi rend="italic">A.P.C.</hi>, xxix,
          154–157.)</note></p>

        <p>The Quene removed on Wensday toward
          <placeName ref="#nonsuch">Nonsuch</placeName> taking
          <persName ref="#caesar-julius">Dr. Cesars</persName><note><persName ref="#caesar-julius">Julius Caesar</persName>
          (knighted 1603), Master of Requests in Ordinary. On September 12
          <persName ref="#elizabeth-i">Queen Elizabeth</persName> visited him at
          <placeName ref="#mitcham">Mitcham</placeName>, Surrey, spent the night there, and dined
          with him the next day.</note> in her way who had provided for her eight severall times.
          <persName ref="#brockett-john">Sir John Brocket</persName><note><persName ref="#brockett-john">Sir
          John Brockett</persName> of Brockett Hall, Hertfordshire. His wife was Ellen Lytton, a
          relative of <persName ref="#lytton-rowland">Rowland Lytton</persName>. His daughter
          Elizabeth was the first wife of
          <persName ref="#carleton-george">George Carleton</persName> and the mother of John
          Carleton, the nephew here mentioned.</note> lies languishing and is thought will not hold
          out long, but whether be better for your nephew that he go or tarry is a question.</p>

        <p>On Thursday your cousin
          <persName ref="#lytton-rowland">Lytton</persName> and I receved your letters of the 29 of
          August and the 8th of this present, which came so fully furnished with ballads, bookes and
          babies that we cannot overcome them yet, specially
          <persName ref="#aldegonde-philip">Aldegondes</persName> tedious discourse.<note><persName ref="#aldegonde-philip">Philip
          van Marnix van Sint Aldegonde</persName> was the author of several religious discourses
          that were in print before 1598.</note> Yf he were now at home I know he wold send you
          many thancks, which I wold faine supplie yf I were as goode at yt as himself, but you
          know my plain dealinge and therefore I hope will expect no ceremonies. He went yesterday
          to <placeName ref="#bletsoe">Bletso</placeName><note>Bletsoe, Bedfordshire, the seat of
          <persName ref="#st-john-oliver">Oliver, third Lord St. John</persName>.</note> to convoy
          the Lords, and
          <persName ref="#st-john-judith">Lady Pelham</persName><note><persName ref="#st-john-judith">Judith</persName>,
          daughter of Oliver, first Lord St. John, and widow of Sir John Pelham of Sandhurst,
          Sussex.</note> that hath lien here this fortnight, and wold faine have drawne me along
          with him, but by goode hap a certain cold and hoarsenes kept me at home, for how well so
          ever they use me, yet me thincks I am out of my element when I am among Lords, and I am
          of Rabelais minde that they looke big <hi rend="italic">comme un millord
          d'Angleterre</hi>.</p>

        <p>I can send you nothing of your privat frends neither can I tell certainly when I shalbe
          at London, but toward the terme have with you to Westminster, till when I bid you farewell
          with my best and kindest wishes.</p>

        <closer>
          <dateline>From <placeName ref="#knebworth">Knebworth</placeName> this
            <date when="1598-09-17">17th of September 1598</date>.</dateline>
          <signed>Yours most assuredly,
            <persName ref="#chamberlain-john">JOHN CHAMBERLAIN</persName>.</signed>
        </closer>

        <postscript>
          <p>To my assured goode frend Master
            <persName ref="#carleton-dudley">Dudley Carleton</persName> attending on the Lord
            Governor of <placeName ref="#ostend">Ostend</placeName> geve these.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div type="editor-note">
        <head>Editor's Note</head>
        <p>Written hastily from Knebworth, the Hertfordshire seat of Rowland Lytton, this brief
          letter is notable for what it withholds as much as what it reports. Chamberlain, caught
          off guard by the messenger's imminent departure, confesses he has no news of his own and
          must borrow a recently received letter to send along. The one piece of court intelligence
          he can confirm is that Essex returned to the Privy Council on September 10—though
          Chamberlain himself does not know the outcome. A brief mention of Sir John Brockett's
          failing health raises the question of what will happen to Carleton's nephew (Brockett's
          grandson John Carleton), a thread that will recur in later letters. The letter's most
          personal passage describes Rowland Lytton escorting Lady Pelham—Judith St. John, a widow
          long connected to the household—to Bletsoe, seat of Oliver, third Lord St. John, while
          Chamberlain stays behind with a cold. His self-deprecating Rabelais quotation—"they look
          grand like an English lord"—reflects his characteristic ambivalence toward aristocratic
          company.</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
