<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Letter from John Chamberlain to Dudley Carleton, 22 November 1598</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editor</resp>
          <name>Brandon Taylor</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Published digitally at earlymodernletters.org. Licensed under CC BY 4.0.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>The Letters of John Chamberlain</title>
          <editor>Norman Egbert McClure</editor>
          <pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>
          <publisher>American Philosophical Society</publisher>
          <date when="1939">1939</date>
          <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
          <biblScope unit="page">53–54</biblScope>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="letter-meta">
        <head>Letter Metadata</head>
        <p><date when="1598-11-22">22 November 1598</date></p>
        <p><placeName ref="#london">London</placeName></p>
        <p><correspDesc>
          <correspAction type="sent">
            <persName ref="#chamberlain-john">John Chamberlain</persName>
            <date when="1598-11-22"/>
            <placeName ref="#london">London</placeName>
          </correspAction>
          <correspAction type="received">
            <persName ref="#carleton-dudley">Dudley Carleton</persName>
            <placeName ref="#ostend">Ostend</placeName>
          </correspAction>
        </correspDesc></p>
      </div>
    </front>

    <body>
      <div type="letter-text">
        <opener>Master Carleton,</opener>

        <p>This longe and permanent abode of westerly windes bringes us no newes but such as we
          least desire to heare of — I meane out of
          <placeName ref="#ireland">Ireland</placeName>, whence messengers come dayly (like Jobs
          servants) laden with yll tidings of new troubles and revokes. The English of
          <placeName ref="#munster">Mounster</placeName> are much blamed for making no better
          proofe of themselves, and geving so easie way to the rebells; and (as goode I telle yt
          you as another)
          <persName ref="#norris-thomas">Sir Thomas Norris</persName><note>Sir Thomas Norris
          (1556–1599), Lord President of Munster from 1597. Chamberlain's report that he took
          the alarm too soon and abandoned his station reflects the widespread English criticism
          of the Munster commanders after the collapse of the plantation in autumn 1598. Norris
          died in July 1599, worn out by the Irish command.</note> hath his part with the rest
          and is thought to have taken the alarme too soone and left his station before there was
          neede, whereby the ennemie was too much incouraged, and those that were well affected or
          stoode indifferent forced to follow the tide. The remedies of these mischeifes go as
          slowly forward as other matters, only it is saide the erle of
          <persName ref="#devereux-robert">Essex</persName> shall go thether about February or
          March with as ample commission as ever any had, the conditions wherof were lost labour
          to set downe because they varie and alter every weeke, and withall his going is not so
          fully resolved but that once in ten dayes yt is in question.</p>

        <p>The day that we looked for
          <persName ref="#stanley-john">Stanlies</persName> arraignment he came not himself but
          sent his forerunner one
          <persName ref="#squire-edward">Squire</persName> that had ben an under purvayer of the
          stable, who being in
          <placeName ref="#spain">Spaine</placeName> was delt withall by one
          <persName ref="#walpole-richard">Walpoole</persName><note>Father Richard Walpole SJ
          (c. 1564–1607), an English Jesuit working in Spain; brother of the martyr Henry Walpole
          (executed 1595). It was Walpole who recruited Squire and provided the poisonous
          preparation. Walpole later denied the whole affair.</note> a Jesuite, to poison the
          Quene and the earle of
          <persName ref="#devereux-robert">Essex</persName>, and accordingly came prepared into
          <placeName ref="#england">England</placeName>, and went with the earle in his owne ship
          the last jorny,<note>The Islands Voyage of 1597, Essex's expedition to the Azores.
          Squire sailed in Essex's own ship, which gave him access to the chair where Essex
          sat.</note> and poisoned the armes or handles of the chaire he used to sit in with a
          confection he had receved of the Jesuite, as likewise he had don the pommell of the
          Quenes saddle not past five dayes before his going to sea: but because nothing succeded
          of yt, the priest thincking he had either chaunged his purpose or bewraied yt, gave
          <persName ref="#stanley-john">Stanly</persName> instructions to accuse him, thereby to
          get him more credit and to be revenged of
          <persName ref="#squire-edward">Squire</persName> for breaking promise. The fellow
          seemed very penitent and confest the whole practise. The Quenes
          <persName ref="#coke-edward">atturney</persName><note>Edward Coke (1552–1634),
          Attorney General from 1594; later Chief Justice of Common Pleas (1606) and of King's
          Bench (1613), and one of the great figures of English common law. The surprise of this
          marriage — Chamberlain notes it with characteristic scepticism — lay in Lady Hatton's
          choosing a man of lesser social standing over the many "large and likely offers" she
          had received.</note> the seventh of this month married the
          <persName ref="#hatton-elizabeth">Lady Hatton</persName><note>Elizabeth Cecil
          (1578–1646), daughter of Thomas Cecil, second Lord Burghley (later first Earl of
          Exeter); widow of Sir William Hatton (d. 1597), nephew and heir of the great
          Christopher Hatton. As Lady Hatton she became one of the leading hostesses of the
          Jacobean court, and her marriage to Coke was notoriously turbulent.</note> to the
          great admiration of all men, that after so many large and likely offers she shold
          decline to a man of his qualitie, and the world will not beleve that yt was without a
          misterie. The day before,
          <persName ref="#packington-john">Sir John Packington</persName><note>Sir John
          Packington (1549–1625), Worcestershire knight, knighted by Essex in 1596; known as
          "Lusty Packington" at court. He married Dorothy Smith, widow of Benedict Barnham,
          a London mercer.</note> maried
          <persName ref="#barnham-dorothy">Mistris Barnham</persName><note>Dorothy Smith
          (dates unknown), daughter of Humphrey Smith, silkman to Queen Elizabeth, and widow of
          Benedict Barnham, a liveryman of the Drapers' Company.</note>, one of our
          <placeName ref="#london">London</placeName> widowes. The erle of
          <persName ref="#wriothesley-henry">Southampton</persName> is come home and for his
          welcome committed to the Fleet,<note>Southampton had returned from France; his
          confinement in the Fleet prison followed from the Queen's continued displeasure at his
          secret marriage to Elizabeth Vernon. Chamberlain adds that he was already rumoured to
          be on the point of release.</note> but I heare he is already upon his delivery.</p>

        <p>The Quene came to
          <placeName ref="#whitehall">Whitehall</placeName> the last weeke, being receved a mile
          out of towne by the Lord Mayor and his bretheren accompanied with 400 velvet cotes and
          chaines of gold. Her days passed without any extraordinarie matter more then running
          and ringing.<note>Running at the ring and bell-ringing were customary celebrations for
          Accession Day (17 November), the anniversary of Elizabeth's accession in 1558; the
          Queen arrived at Whitehall on 14 November, three days before the annual
          festivities.</note> Your brother
          <persName ref="#carleton-george">Carleton</persName> hath ben in towne most part of
          this terme but is now gon. Other newes we have none so that with all my best wishes I
          bid you farewell.</p>

        <closer>
          <dateline>From <placeName ref="#london">London</placeName> this
            <date when="1598-11-22">22th of November 1598</date>.</dateline>
          <signed>Yours most assuredly,
            <persName ref="#chamberlain-john">JOHN CHAMBERLAIN</persName>.</signed>
        </closer>

        <postscript>
          <p>To my very goode frend Master
            <persName ref="#carleton-dudley">Dudley Carleton</persName> attending on the Lord
            Governor of <placeName ref="#ostend">Ostend</placeName> geve these.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
