<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Letter from John Chamberlain to Dudley Carleton, 17 January 1599</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editor</resp>
          <name>Brandon Taylor</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Published digitally at earlymodernletters.org. Licensed under CC BY 4.0.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>The Letters of John Chamberlain</title>
          <editor>Norman Egbert McClure</editor>
          <pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>
          <publisher>American Philosophical Society</publisher>
          <date when="1939">1939</date>
          <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
          <biblScope unit="page">62–65</biblScope>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="letter-meta">
        <head>Letter Metadata</head>
        <p><date when="1599-01-17">17 January 1599</date></p>
        <p><placeName ref="#london">London</placeName></p>
        <p><correspDesc>
          <correspAction type="sent">
            <persName ref="#chamberlain-john">John Chamberlain</persName>
            <date when="1599-01-17"/>
            <placeName ref="#london">London</placeName>
          </correspAction>
          <correspAction type="received">
            <persName ref="#carleton-dudley">Dudley Carleton</persName>
            <placeName ref="#ostend">Ostend</placeName>
          </correspAction>
        </correspDesc></p>
      </div>
    </front>

    <body>
      <div type="letter-text">
        <opener>Master Carleton,</opener>

        <p>Though I looke in a manner dayly for your comming over, yet because many
          accidents may chaunge your course, or defer your passage for a time, I will not
          omit this present occasion, but salute you after my accustomed manner, the rather
          because I have neither heard of you nor written since the end of Christmas.</p>

        <p>And to begin with the first, the Quene on Twelvth day to close up the holy dayes,
          and do the
          <persName ref="#cragius-nicholaus">Danish Ambassador</persName><note>Nicholaus
          Cragius (1550–1602), Danish diplomat and classical scholar, in London to press for
          the restitution promised in Perkins's half-answer from Denmark (see Letters 13–14).
          The Queen's choice to dance with Essex before the ambassador was deliberate
          political theatre — displaying her favourite and signalling his fitness for
          command.</note> honor, daunct with the erle of
          <persName ref="#devereux-robert">Essex</persName> very richly and freshly attired.
          Since, there fell out a great unkindnes twixt the erle and the
          <persName ref="#howard-charles">Lord Admirall</persName><note>Charles Howard, first
          Earl of Nottingham (1536–1624); Lord High Admiral since 1585 and the principal
          commander against the Armada. His quarrel with Essex over military patronage is
          one symptom of the broader competition between older Elizabethan magnates and
          Essex's client network for control of army appointments.</note> about
          <persName ref="#woodhouse-william">Sir William Woodhouse</persName><note>An officer
          seeking a company in the Low Countries; the disputed regiment was that of Sir Thomas
          Knolles. The quarrel turned on whether Essex's Irish patronage extended to
          appointments in the Low Countries garrisons — the Lord Admiral evidently thought
          not.</note> that was to have a companie in the
          <placeName ref="#low-countries">Lowe Countries</placeName> in
          <persName ref="#knolles-thomas">Sir Thomas Knolles</persName> regiment. The matter
          is yet not taken up, and some high wordes passed. The erles jorny for
          <placeName ref="#ireland">Ireland</placeName> is somwhat prolonged, for his
          vitaylers that had order to make theyre provisions for February are now put over
          till March.</p>

        <p>He shall cary a great troupe of gallants with him, yf all go that are spoken of,
          as the erles of
          <persName ref="#stanley-william">Darbie</persName><note>William Stanley, sixth Earl
          of Derby (1561–1642).</note>,
          <persName ref="#manners-roger">Rutland</persName><note>Roger Manners, fifth Earl of
          Rutland (1576–1612); a young Essex favourite and Shakespeare's Cambridge
          contemporary.</note> and
          <persName ref="#wriothesley-henry">Southampton</persName>, the Lords
          <persName ref="#windsor-henry">Windsore</persName><note>Henry, fifth Lord Windsor
          (1562–1605).</note>,
          <persName ref="#grey-thomas-wilton">Gray</persName>,
          <persName ref="#touchet-george">Audeley</persName><note>George Touchet, eighteenth
          Lord Audley (c. 1551–1617); created Earl of Castlehaven in 1616.</note> and
          <persName ref="#cromwell-edward">Cromwell</persName>, wherof
          <persName ref="#gorges-ferdinando">Sir Ferdinando Gorge</persName><note>Sir
          Ferdinando Gorges (c. 1568–1647), named Lord Marshall of Essex's army. After Essex's
          failure in Ireland and his involvement in the 1601 uprising, Gorges turned crown's
          evidence against Essex. He later became the principal promoter of English colonisation
          in New England and the founding governor of the Province of Maine.</note>
          is named to be Lord Marshall of the army besides knights sans number; to be
          Sergeant Major,
          <persName ref="#danvers-henry">Sir Henry Davers</persName> to have the leading of
          300 horse,
          <persName ref="#danvers-charles">Sir Charles Davers</persName>,
          <persName ref="#percy-charles">Sir Charles Percy</persName><note>Third son of Henry
          Percy, ninth Earl of Northumberland ('the Wizard Earl').</note>,
          <persName ref="#blount-charles">Sir Charles Blunt</persName>,
          <persName ref="#jermyn-thomas">Sir Thomas Germin</persName><note>Sir Thomas Jermyn
          (c. 1573–1645), of Rushbrooke, Suffolk.</note>,
          <persName ref="#ratcliffe-alexander">Sir Alexander Ratcliffe</persName> and
          <persName ref="#egerton-john">Egerton</persName><note>Sir John Egerton
          (c. 1579–1649), elder son of Sir Thomas Egerton, Lord Keeper; later first Earl of
          Bridgewater.</note>,
          <persName ref="#blount-christopher">Sir Christofer Blunt</persName><note>Sir
          Christopher Blount (c. 1555–1601), Essex's stepfather, having married his widowed
          mother Lettice Knollys. Among Essex's most loyal followers; executed after the
          1601 uprising.</note>,
          <persName ref="#wingfield-edward">Sir Edward Wingfeld</persName>
          and ten or twelve others of that standing looke to be served too. But yt is saide
          the erle geves few places nor bestowes offices to any as yet, because he will hold
          his followers in hart till he have them there: many that wish well to the jorny
          have no great conceit of yt seing many raw youthes preasse for the greatest
          charges.</p>

        <p>Here was speach that the erle of
          <persName ref="#fitzgerald-gerald">Kildare</persName><note>Gerald Fitzgerald,
          fourteenth Earl of Kildare (1559–1612); a Pale-loyal Irish nobleman restored to the
          earldom in 1585. His 'standing upon termes' suggests wavering loyalty under rebel
          pressure, though he ultimately remained on the English side.</note> and the Lord of
          <persName ref="#nugent-christopher">Delvin</persName><note>Christopher Nugent,
          fourteenth Lord Delvin (c. 1544–1602); another Old English magnate of the Pale whose
          equivocation in early 1599 alarmed the Dublin government.</note> began to stand upon
          termes and the cheife rebells began to geve doubtfull aunswers and put water in
          theyre wine and to proceed with more temper. Ships from the
          <placeName ref="#low-countries">Lowe Countries</placeName> bound for the victualing
          of <placeName ref="#ireland">Ireland</placeName>, having touched the coast of
          <placeName ref="#portugal">Portingale</placeName>, were by weather put into
          <placeName ref="#plymouth">Plimmouth</placeName> — bringing with them some of
          <persName ref="#leveson-richard">Sir Richard Lewson</persName>'s escaped Hanseatic
          vessels, which could now be detained and inspected. The Duke of
          <persName ref="#medici-ferdinand">Florence</persName><note>Ferdinand I de' Medici,
          Grand Duke of Tuscany (1549–1609); his barring of English merchants was part of the
          wider European backlash against English privateering.</note> hath barred our nation
          from traffike in his territories, and yt is feared the Venetians and the French
          king will serve us in the same sort.</p>

        <p>The Quene is very angry with
          <persName ref="#gerard-thomas">Sir Thomas Gerrard</persName> for the escape of one
          <persName ref="#blackwell-george">Blackwell</persName><note>George Blackwell
          (c. 1545–1613), appointed archpriest over the English secular Catholic clergy by
          Pope Clement VIII in March 1598. His escape from the Marshalsea prison in Southwark
          (a state prison south of the Thames) was an embarrassment to the Privy Council,
          which had detained him as part of its surveillance of the Catholic ecclesiastical
          hierarchy in England.</note> an archpriest out of the Marshallsee. There was a plot
          layde by certain Jesuites and preists to murther or poison the Scottish kinge, and
          yt is confessed by some that are taken. The Scottish king had a sore bruise with
          the fall of an horse and was let bloude fowre times.</p>

        <p>The newes comes now very hot that the king of
          <placeName ref="#portugal">Portingale</placeName> that was said to be slaine in the
          battell is at
          <placeName ref="#venice">Venice</placeName>, and hath made so goode triall of
          himself that the Venetians allowe him, and maintaine almost fowrescore with
          fowretene more at theyre charge. They say he tells very straunge stories, how he
          got up into the mountaines, and so by many adventures and <hi rend="italic">per tot
          discrimina</hi> in this longe pilgrimage (wherin he hath ben taken, bought and sold
          twelve or thirtene times) got at last to
          <placeName ref="#venice">Venice</placeName>, where he tells them all that was
          negotiated twixt him and them either by letters or ambassadors, since he was of any
          goode remembraunce, so many perticulers as are thought infallible, with
          testimonies; and that his confessor is come out of
          <placeName ref="#portugal">Portingale</placeName> and upon conference avoucheth all
          to be true that he saith, touching what passed twixt them in confession both the
          day before the battell and at other times. We run away with all, as though all were
          our owne, and are easilie persuaded to beleve what we wold have. What will come of
          yt God knowes, but yt were a happy turne for Christendome yf yt were true, but yt
          will by no meanes sincke downe with me, but that still I feare he wilbe cousened
          and trussed up in the end.<note>The claim that Sebastian I of Portugal — killed at
          the Battle of Alcácer Quibir (4 August 1578) against the Moroccan sultan — had
          survived was the foundation of a messianic movement known as Sebastianism. Several
          pretenders emerged across Europe in the following decades. This Venetian claimant
          was investigated by the Venetian Senate and ultimately rejected as an impostor from
          Calabria. Chamberlain's scepticism — 'we run away with all, as though all were our
          owne, and are easilie persuaded to beleve what we wold have' — is among his most
          pointed comments on credulity and wishful thinking. Philip III's reported march into
          Portugal was probably defensive: a credible Sebastianist claimant would threaten
          Spain's 1580 annexation of the Portuguese crown.</note> The king of
          <placeName ref="#spain">Spaine</placeName> is saide to be going into
          <placeName ref="#portugal">Portingale</placeName> with a 1000 horse and 3000 foote
          upon this rumor, but I rather thincke yt is to be receved there and crowned.</p>

        <p><persName ref="#drury-dru">Sir Dru Drury</persName><note>Sir Dru Drury
          (c. 1531–1617), Gentleman Usher of the Privy Chamber throughout Elizabeth's reign.
          His 'old remitter' suggests a prior period of restriction from court attendance, now
          lifted.</note> is in his old remitter and commanded to wait in his place of
          gentleman usher of the privie chamber. There is a mariage spoken of twixt the Lord
          <persName ref="#brooke-henry">Cobham</persName> and the Countesse of
          <persName ref="#fitzgerald-frances-kildare">Kildare</persName>, and betwene his
          lame brother
          <persName ref="#brooke-george">Master George Brooke</persName><note>George Brooke
          (c. 1568–1603), younger brother of Henry Brooke, eighth Lord Cobham; he married
          Elizabeth, daughter of Thomas, fifth Lord Burgh. He was later executed in connection
          with the Main Plot against James I in 1603.</note> and the Lord Borroughs eldest
          daughter. Yt is saide likewise that
          <persName ref="#woodhouse-william">Sir Will. Woodhouse</persName> hath married the
          <persName ref="#southwell-lady">Lady Southwell</persName><note>Widow of Sir Robert
          Southwell. Chamberlain contradicts this report in Letter 18.</note>, and the
          <persName ref="#paulet-william-iv">Lord Marquis</persName><note>William Paulet,
          fourth Marquis of Winchester (c. 1561–1628), who had just inherited the title on
          his father's death in November 1598. Chamberlain's pointed aside — 'before he
          buried' his father — implies the new Marquis rushed into a hasty marriage while
          still in formal mourning.</note> (before he buried) hath married a youth not full
          eightene yeares old, younger sonne to
          <persName ref="#fleetwood-william">Master Fleetwoode</persName><note>William
          Fleetwood (knighted 1603), receiver of the Court of Wards.</note> receiver of the
          court of wardes.</p>

        <p><persName ref="#arundell-matthew">Sir Mathew Arundell</persName><note>Sir Matthew
          Arundell of Wardour Castle, Wiltshire (d. January 1599). His bequests — £2,000 for
          a causeway near Sherborne, £2,000 to the poor — follow the conventional charitable
          patterns of a man of his standing.</note> is died these holy dayes and hath left
          much to goode uses, as 2000<hi rend="italic">li</hi> to the making of a cawsey
          about <placeName ref="#sherborne">Sherborne</placeName>, and
          2000<hi rend="italic">li</hi> to the poore, and many other legacies of like
          nature. The
          <persName ref="#cope-frances">Lady Cope</persName><note>Frances Cope (née Lytton),
          sister of Rowland Lytton of Knebworth and wife of Sir Anthony Cope of Hanwell,
          Oxfordshire; first cousin of Dudley Carleton and evidently a figure of real warmth
          for Chamberlain — 'mine old mistris' meaning his former patroness, not a romantic
          attachment. She died on Twelfth Even (January 5, 1599).</note> your cousen and
          mine old mistris (as I heare) left the world on Twelvth Even and
          <persName ref="#spenser-edmund">Spencer</persName><note>Edmund Spenser
          (c. 1552–1599), poet and colonial administrator in Ireland; author of
          <hi rend="italic">The Faerie Queene</hi> (1590, 1596). He arrived in London in
          December 1598 carrying dispatches from Sir Thomas Norris, Lord President of Munster,
          and died at Westminster on Saturday, January 16, 1599. His funeral was, as Camden
          records, 'at the charges of the Earle of Essex, his Hearse being carried by Poets,
          and mournfull Verses thrown into his Tombe' (<hi rend="italic">Annales</hi>,
          p. 501). Chamberlain names him as 'our principall poet' and moves on without
          ceremony — a plain tribute that may be more eloquent for its brevity.</note> our
          principall poet comming lately out of
          <placeName ref="#ireland">Ireland</placeName> died at Westminster on Saturday
          last.</p>

        <p><persName ref="#neville-henry">Master Nevill</persName> goes within these eight
          or ten dayes into
          <placeName ref="#france">Fraunce</placeName> and hath won
          <persName ref="#winwood-ralph">Master Winwoode</persName><note>Ralph Winwood
          (c. 1563–1617), diplomat; he served as secretary to Henry Nevill on his embassy to
          France (1599–1601) and later became Secretary of State under James I (1614–1617).
          His attachment to Essex's patronage network here marks the beginning of his public
          career.</note> at my Lord of
          <persName ref="#devereux-robert">Essex</persName> commandment to beare him companie
          and be about him. Yf I had more you see I am no niggard and therfore without
          further ceremonies I bid you farewell.</p>

        <closer>
          <dateline>From <placeName ref="#london">London</placeName> this
            <date when="1599-01-17">17th of January 1598</date>.</dateline>
          <signed>Yours most assuredly,
            <persName ref="#chamberlain-john">JOHN CHAMBERLAIN</persName>.</signed>
        </closer>

        <postscript>
          <p>To my very goode frend Master
            <persName ref="#carleton-dudley">Dudley Carleton</persName> attending on the Lord
            Governor of <placeName ref="#ostend">Ostend</placeName> geve these.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
