<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Letter from John Chamberlain to Dudley Carleton, 20 December 1598</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editor</resp>
          <name>Brandon Taylor</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Published digitally at earlymodernletters.org. Licensed under CC BY 4.0.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>The Letters of John Chamberlain</title>
          <editor>Norman Egbert McClure</editor>
          <pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>
          <publisher>American Philosophical Society</publisher>
          <date when="1939">1939</date>
          <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
          <biblScope unit="page">58–60</biblScope>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="letter-meta">
        <head>Letter Metadata</head>
        <p><date when="1598-12-20">20 December 1598</date></p>
        <p><placeName ref="#london">London</placeName></p>
        <p><correspDesc>
          <correspAction type="sent">
            <persName ref="#chamberlain-john">John Chamberlain</persName>
            <date when="1598-12-20"/>
            <placeName ref="#london">London</placeName>
          </correspAction>
          <correspAction type="received">
            <persName ref="#carleton-dudley">Dudley Carleton</persName>
            <placeName ref="#ostend">Ostend</placeName>
          </correspAction>
        </correspDesc></p>
      </div>
    </front>

    <body>
      <div type="letter-text">
        <opener>Master Carleton,</opener>

        <p>The world is litle or nothing chaunged here since I wrote last, only the Quene is
          resolved to kepe Christmas at
          <placeName ref="#whitehall">Whitehall</placeName>, and the matters of
          <placeName ref="#ireland">Ireland</placeName> stand at a stay or rather go backward, for
          the erle of
          <persName ref="#devereux-robert">Essex</persName> his jorny thether that was in
          suspence is now they say quite dasht — not that there is any other order taken, but only
          that things shall still drive on there as they may, and perhaps they hope
          <hi rend="italic">cunctando restitutere rem</hi>,<note>An allusion to the Roman
          dictator Quintus Fabius Maximus, whose delaying tactics against Hannibal gave rise
          to the motto <hi rend="italic">cunctando restituit rem</hi> — "by delaying he restored
          the commonwealth." Chamberlain deploys it sardonically: Fabian delay may suit some
          crises, but not, he implies, <hi rend="italic">deplorata valetudine</hi> — a condition
          already desperate.</note> which all men take to be a wronge course in
          <hi rend="italic">deplorata valetudine</hi> and so desperate a disease. From Tuesday
          last till Sunday yt held fast and firm that the erle of
          <persName ref="#devereux-robert">Essex</persName> was to go, and all things were
          accordingly setled and set downe, but a sodain alteration came on Sunday night the reason
          wherof is yet kept secret. Some say the Quene had promised to forgeve him twelve thowsand
          pound debt due by his father, and 20000<hi rend="italic">li</hi> he ought her himself for
          cochenilla<note>Cochineal, a red dye imported from Spanish America and highly prized in
          the Elizabethan textile trade. Essex apparently owed the crown a large sum arising from
          a licence or transaction in cochineal since his last journey — possibly the Islands
          Voyage of 1597.</note> since his last jorny, which belike was mistaken, for the Quene
          sayes she meant but the forbearance of yt, and that yt shold not be called upon in his
          absence; but whether yt were this or some other matter all is turnd upside downe. He and
          <persName ref="#cecil-robert">Master Secretarie</persName> have so goode leysure that
          they plie the tables hard in the presence chamber and play so round game as yf
          <placeName ref="#ireland">Ireland</placeName> were to be recovered at Irish.<note>Irish
          was a board game resembling backgammon. The image of Essex and Cecil gambling at court
          while Ireland burns is one of Chamberlain's sharpest ironies.</note> The rebells in the
          mean time have don many outragious and slaine lately
          <persName ref="#moore-thomas">Sir Tho. Moore</persName><note>Sir Thomas Moore, nicknamed
          "the lying knight," an English settler or officer in Ireland killed by the rebels in
          late 1598. The mocking sobriquet is unusual; Chamberlain seems to relay it with some
          relish.</note> (surnamed the lieng knight) and
          <persName ref="#dukes-wife">his wife that was Sir Henry Dukes daughter</persName><note>
          The wife of Sir Thomas Moore, daughter of Sir Henry Duke; Chamberlain describes her as
          "the properest gentlewoman of Ireland that I saw," suggesting he had met her personally
          at some point.</note> and the properest gentlewoman of
          <placeName ref="#ireland">Ireland</placeName> that I saw, and hurt
          <persName ref="#gifford-captain">Cap. Gifford</persName>, and 800 men went to scowre the
          country about
          <placeName ref="#dublin">Dublin</placeName>. They have likewise overthrowne or defaced
          fowre or five strong places or castles as they call them.
          <persName ref="#bingham-richard">Sir Richard Bingham</persName> with twenty went to the
          <placeName ref="#naas">Nasse</placeName>, which is not past ten or twelve miles from
          <placeName ref="#dublin">Dublin</placeName>, but before he came thither he was so
          incountred and beset that he was fain to retire without attempting further, and fell sicke
          at
          <placeName ref="#dublin">Dublin</placeName>, where some say he is dead.</p>

        <p><persName ref="#perkins-christopher">Doctor Parkins</persName> at his first comming out
          of
          <placeName ref="#denmark">Denmarke</placeName> made his bragges that he had brought
          matters there to a goode passe, but all he hath don is only a promise of 40000 dollers to
          be restored on condition his subjects may be satisfied for such injuries as they have
          receved, and to that purpose he sent an ambassador along with him who had audience on
          Sunday last, but his message was nothing pleasing, being for the most part a complaint of
          our piracies. And as Dr. Parkins returned with half an aunswer, so they say
          <persName ref="#cary-george">Master Cary</persName><note>George Cary, sent on an embassy
          to Poland; he returned having failed to secure any audience with the Polish court.
          Chamberlain treats the paired failures of the Danish and Polish missions as symptomatic
          of the general mismanagement of English affairs abroad.</note> is come out of
          <placeName ref="#poland">Poland</placeName> with none at all, nor could get no audience.
          The ships that were staide by
          <persName ref="#leveson-richard">Sir Richard Lewson</persName> stole away most of them
          the night following, and left him <hi rend="italic">con tanto di naso</hi><note>Italian
          idiom: literally "with so much nose," meaning left looking foolish — equivalent to the
          English "left holding the bag." The remark extends Chamberlain's caustic survey of
          English incompetence at home and abroad.</note> as the Italian saith, so sutable is the
          managing of our affaires both at home and abrode. Fowre or five shippes of your Dunkerke
          neighbours gave a great alarme lately to
          <placeName ref="#yorkshire">Yorkeshire</placeName> and made them fire theyre beacons, but
          that was all the harme they did; yt is thought they meant to have landed and taken some
          prisoners to help to redeem theyre governor.<note>Don Francisco de Aquillar Alverado,
          Governor of Dunkirk, had been a prisoner at Ostend since 1597 — the very garrison where
          Carleton was serving. Chamberlain's aside "your Dunkerke neighbours" acknowledges this
          local detail.</note> We heare the States make huge levies of mony and meane to be masters
          of the feild the next sommer whatsoever yt cost them. The French king is sending to the
          <placeName ref="#rome">Pope</placeName> to determine the controversie of the Marquisat of
          <placeName ref="#saluzzo">Saluces</placeName>,<note>The Marquisate of Saluzzo (Saluces),
          an Alpine territory taken by Savoy from France in 1588. Henri IV was pressing for its
          return or equivalent compensation; the matter was eventually settled by the Treaty of
          Lyon in 1601.</note> for that in the treaty of peace that was referred to his
          arbitrement. The loane of 150000<hi rend="italic">li</hi> makes many of our citizens
          shrincke and pull in theyre hornes, but yet yt goes forward and they must furnish yt;
          and some whispering there is that when that is don we shall heare of a
          benevolence.<note>A benevolence was a "voluntary" gift exacted by the crown from wealthy
          subjects — technically a free gift, in practice a forced levy. The rumour of one coming
          on top of the current loan reflects Chamberlain's dim view of royal fiscal
          management.</note> Yf we be driven to these shifts alredy God knowes how we shall hold
          hereafter, and I marvayle that they which knew these wants did hearken no more after the
          peace when they might have had yt with goode conditions.</p>

        <p>You see how confidently I write to you of all things, but I hope you kepe yt to
          yourself, and then there is no daunger; and I am so used to a libertie and fredome of
          speach when I converse or write to my frends that I cannot easilie leave yt. Your brother
          and sister
          <persName ref="#williams-alexander">Williams</persName> marvaile they heare not from you.
          I have had much ado to excuse myself this Christmas from
          <placeName ref="#knebworth">Knebworth</placeName><note>The Hertfordshire seat of
          <persName ref="#lytton-rowland">Rowland Lytton</persName>, where Chamberlain often
          stayed.</note> and Ascot,<note>The Oxfordshire house of
          <persName ref="#dormer-michael">Michael Dormer</persName>.</note> but specially from
          <placeName ref="#knebworth">Knebworth</placeName>, the rather because
          <persName ref="#cope-walter">Wat Cope</persName><note>Walter Cope (c. 1553–1614),
          administrator and collector; secretary to Robert Cecil and later keeper of Whitehall
          Palace. He assembled a famous cabinet of curiosities in his house on Kensington High
          Street. Knighted in 1603.</note> and his wife,
          <persName ref="#beeston-hugh">Hugh Beeston</persName>, and
          <persName ref="#carew-george">Master Carew</persName> go thether; but upon some occasions
          I am growne so privat that I stirre not abrode, nor mean to do but to live at home like
          a snaile in the shell. And so, wishing you a goode new yeare and many, I end.</p>

        <closer>
          <dateline>From <placeName ref="#london">London</placeName> this
            <date when="1598-12-20">20th of December 1598</date>.</dateline>
          <signed>Yours most assuredly,
            <persName ref="#chamberlain-john">JOHN CHAMBERLAIN</persName>.</signed>
        </closer>

        <postscript>
          <p>To my very goode frend Master
            <persName ref="#carleton-dudley">Dudley Carleton</persName> attending on the Lord
            Governor of <placeName ref="#ostend">Ostende</placeName> geve these.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
